[music]
Hey. Hey. Hey.
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome back to the ask
show. Today we discuss the world of
empires, kingdoms and what is that word?
Vasals. But before we do that, let me
see who all is there on the live chat.
Let me greet some of you. I can see
Ankita Kachap, Himmanshu Rajohit, Meit
Mystery 92 from Australia, Swami from
Jaipur, Avin 3174, Koma list, Vikash PJ,
good evening. Amin anime Barati, Apex
News Network from Assam, good to see
you. History Go1, uh, Udb Sharma, Akuma,
T6N, Freedom from Outcome from Canada,
good to see you, sir. Uh, Sumit,
Namaskar. Uh Swami Sudhir Kumar Juan
Baskar Bandit from Jaipur. Good to see
you. Meet Mistri a real painter
minimalist maverick. Sachin Yadav Dwit
Ashwani
Shankar Mahadevan Daran Patel
Geopolitical Dway from Indor good
evening Bhaskar Bandit once again
minimalist Maverick Tanesh Pandi Crazy
Brain good evening Dara from Jaipur good
to have you Priyanka Javalia good
evening ma'am lone walker hello Swami
Duta good evening makan69 hello Drit
Dr. Harsha P. Naidu, good evening. Good
evening. A real Vladimir Putin is here.
Dan Priya Pri from Oisha. Jagan Jaganat.
Hersa Linga.
Hersa Linga Utla. Okay. Sorry. Uh Neil
from Odisha. Gopinat Misra Kalist once
again. Gravity Kah good to see you.
Anishh Paratia
Anindia Bhacharia. Hello. Pranav 581.
Manisha Kardosu. Namaste. Namaste. Sai
Nirup namaste Dr. Dilly Nitesh Boru
Boruto
5835 good evening uh D Vikrian hello
animesh Paul once again uncertainty
principle good evening Vikash PJ once
again Deepika Mishra hello Geopolit once
again uh who else do we have um history
go yes u U N4M
[laughter]
uh Patamesh DH B18 18 ready always
ready. All right, good to see that.
Ready, always ready. And Bushan Bushan
Babar
and everybody else. All right, good to
have you all. Author Santo Rana is also
here from Odisha. Lots of people from
Odisha. Good to see that. Um, okay. So,
let's get going with some questions. I'm
going to take questions about
geopolitics and world affairs today. Uh
Saga is here finding uh finding myself.
Shishti Sap Sapkot is here from
Siliguri. Nice place. Good to have you.
Good to have you ma'am. Luffy Chan from
Canada.
All right. I Yeah. So let's take some
questions. I'm going to discuss
geopolitics today. Okay. Uh so please
don't ask questions beyond from beyond
geopolitics. Today we discussed
geopolitics. Next week we're going to
take other other topics as well. Maybe
we'll do a science special or maybe a
space special like people have been
requesting. We can do that. So let's
what questions do we have? I'll take
questions from the super chats first of
all. Basar Bandit says namaskarum. Hope
you're well. I'm well. I hope you're
well too. Okay. What's the question?
Could you outline the civil war in
Sudan? Okay. Why is it geopolitically
crucial? Because of its c close
proximity to the Swiss canal, global
trade or natural resources or more?
What's the deal?
This is a topic I haven't discussed thus
far. right on on this channel. The the
the civil war in Sudan. So I could tell
you, okay, let's see how how it feels
when I say say explain it this way. The
civil war in Sudan is a conflict between
the
RSF
and the Sudan Armed Forces, SAF. The RSF
and the SAF. The SAF is the government.
The RSF are kind of like rebels and they
are fighting each other. And that's why
we have a civil war in Sudan. And both
are supported from by from external both
are supported by external actors. Does
it make any sense what I just explained?
I threw around some words RSF, SAF.
They're fighting each other. Does it
make any sense? Now, let me explain it
in in a different way. Hopefully, it
makes more sense. Let's go to the map.
As always, I must put the map on the
screen to explain the context. Okay,
let's go to the map and understand what
hell what the hell is happening here.
We're discussing Sudhal. So if we are in
India, we go westwards. We cross the sea
of Sarah. We come to the horn of Africa
and we go further west and there we have
Sudan. This nation here in the south of
Sudan, we have something called South
Sudan. So what is the deal with this
with this region this part of Africa? So
first of all the broader context if you
look at the northern regions of Africa
these were historically occupied
colonized whatever you want to call that
they were historically occupied and
colonized by the Arabs
which because of which in the northern
parts of Africa you will have primarily
Islamic or Muslim populations.
the southern parts of Africa below the
Sahel region, south of the Sahel region,
you typically have more people who are
converted to Christianity by the
European occupiers who occupied Africa
in the 18th, 19th and 20th centuries and
so on. So the further south you go, the
more people you will find who are
converted to Christianity. Overall, very
few people
are left in Africa who still follow the
ancient African religions. It's mostly
Islam and Christianity. Northern
northern parts of Africa you have Islam
primarily Islam and southern parts of
Africa you primarily have Christianity
the dividing line is kind of the the
division the color division here you
know the desert versus the green parts
kind of roughly kind of like that now
when it comes to Sudan okay now that we
understand that let's understand the
demographics of the nation of Sudan the
northern part of Sudan is primarily
Islamic primarily Muslim populations the
southern part of Sudan uh it's primarily
non-Muslim I would say about 50 60%
Christians and the rest would practice
indigenous African religions right now
you can see that the capital city of
Sudan Kartum is in the northern kind of
in the northern half of Sudan if we
forget that South Sudan is a different
entity today and if we see Sudan and and
South Sudan as as one single entity like
like it used to be then you will say
that Kartum is in the north and because
of that it's primarily Islamic. Okay.
Now,
so Sudan was ruled by the Ottomans, by
the Arabs and so on. From the 19th
century onwards, it was ruled by the
British, the Egyptians as well. And in
the 20th century, until which year was
it? It was, I think, the year of the
Suez crisis. 56 was it? Probably around
1956. Until that time, you had the
Egyptians and British jointly ruling
Sudan.
All right.
Now when Sudan became independent most
likely in 1956 you can look up the exact
date the exact year I mean so when Sudan
became independent there was this
conflict about who's going to rule Sudan
is Sudan going to be an Islamic nation
is it going to be a secular nation and
obviously uh the people in the north
they wanted Sudan to be an Islamic
nation uh so the government that took
took over in Kartum in northern Sudan um
they they imposed Sharia on Sudan and
because of that you had uh mass protests
and revolts and whatnot in the south
because they did not want to be under
Sharia law and that's why we had you had
civil war like situations and the
northern the government of Sudan which
was based out of the northern part the
out of Kartum they
used all kinds of nasty tactics to to
retain power uh so that was the
situation in the 1950s all the way to
the 1980s civil war and lots of
atrocities and whatnot. In the 1980s and
and there onwards a c a set of militias
were empowered by the government to to
oppress the people who did not want
Islamic rule and so on. And these
militias were called the Janjawid
militias. Janjawid I don't know what it
means. Whatever it means janjawed.
And they carried out all kinds of
horrific atrocities on the people of
Southern and even even western Sudan,
Darur, the Darur region of Sudan which
is in the western part of Sudan. So
eventually South Sudan seceded in Sudan.
You can look up which year it happened.
Okay, but that's what happens. And then
whatever is left of Sudan, you still
have a southern part in which you have
primarily non-Muslim people. So in the
21st century from 2002 2003 onwards
maybe 2005 onwards whichever it is year
it is there is a terrible conflict in
Darur in southern southern Sudan in
which these Arabic
so-called Arabic militias called the
called the Junjab that I mentioned they
committed all kinds of horrific
atrocities massacres genocide whatever
on the people who did not want to be
under Islamic rule maybe a couple of
couple of million people would have
civilians mainly. Okay. So that has been
the situation. Now fast forward
to the 2010s. So the Janjawid these
people who identify as Arabs they are
now transformed into something called
the RSF rapid support force which is a
paramilitary force which is in in
alliance with the Sudanis armed forces
the SAF.
Now you understand SAF and RSF. So the
RSF is the rebranded Janja with militias
consolidated together and they are kind
of like an auxiliary force at this point
in time 2010s early they are kind of an
auxiliary force to the Sudan armed
forces but then these two sides become
competitors eventually. Now in 2019
uh the president of of Sudan his name is
Bash Bashir whatever his name was he was
ousted by the Sudan armed forces
and I'm not sure who's ruling Sudan
right now must be some general of some
kind okay doesn't matter who's ruling it
it's the and and then what you have is
that there is a conflict between the RSF
and the Sudaris armed forces
um the in 2019 2020 maybe 23 around that
time There were talks to integrate the
two u the two forces the RSF and the SAF
into one single integrated integrated
unit but there were too many differences
and there were too many competing uh
agendas so it did not work out and today
the civil war in Sudan is a civil war
between the Sudan armed forces and the
rapid support forces. Now it is alleged
that the Sudan armed forces are
supported by certain external actors and
the RSF are also supported by certain
external actors. And who is caught in
between? It is the innocent civilians
who and there's a horrific uh
humanitarian crisis in Sudan. Now why
would external actors support the SAF or
the RSF? Why? And since 2023
there's been this you know back and
forth kind of battle battles going on
the lines on the map are like Pink Floyd
would say they moved from side to side
that sort of thing you know that
sometimes Kartum is in the hands of the
RSF sometimes it's in the hands of the
SAF that sort of thing it's going on
back and forth but why would external
actors
why would they support
one of the two forces in Sudan well the
thing about Africa the fantastic thing
about Africa is that it is so rich
in natural resources, mineral wealth. If
you talk about Sudan, what sort of
mineral wealth does it have?
The golden metal, gold. There's plenty
of gold in Sudan. And whoever controls
the land of Sudan gets to extract the
gold. So it is alleged that the Sudan
armed forces, the SAF, it is alleged
that they are supported by the United
States and somebody else. And it is
alleged that the the RSF is supported by
allegedly Russia and allegedly some some
specific Gulf nation allegedly. Okay,
that's the that's what is being said
about this. Uh so the RSF today is said
to be slightly more secular than the
SAF. The Sudhan armed forces are purely
Islamist and the RSF are more rapid
support forces are more pragmatic. Uh
but whatever it is both are overall
you could say they will bring Sharia law
if they take power. That's essentially
the situation. So that is the civil war
in Sudan. Now I hope it makes sense once
I have put the entire history in
perspective. Okay. And it's all about uh
control of resources in the nation in
Sudhan. That's the deal in Africa. These
African nations are are sadly tragically
today dirt poor because of the couple of
past centuries of foreign occupation and
destruction. So these nations are dirt
poor but they are tremendously wealthy
in natural resources. And that's what
external actors want. And that's why
they support either militias or they
support dictatorships. So you pay the
dictator a certain amount of money every
year. You give them some prestigious
whatever thing. Yeah. You know, some
honors or whatever you Yeah. That sort
of thing. And then if you do that then
they will be happy to sell out their
country parcel by parcel to you. That's
how it goes. So that is the deal. And of
course it is kind of the nation is kind
of close to the S canal but it's not
about the S canal. It's about the
natural resources that Sudan has. So who
would like it? Everybody would want it.
The US would want it. The Russians would
want it. Maybe the Chinese would want
it. But who are the players involved?
It is alleged that it's it's the
Americans on one side and the Russians
on on another side and other actors also
may or may not be involved allegedly.
That is the deal
about the civil war. that's going on in
Sudan. It is a horrific humanitarian
situation. Tragic and it's going on and
we don't know what the outcome is going
to be. Right? That's the deal. Okay.
Hope that explains it.
WBR says in the operation spiderweb, why
did Ukraine avoid attacking the most
modern Tupolev 160 bomber? Your opinion
on Trump's latest peace deal seen as a
surrender of Ukraine to Russia.
Okay, look. Uh,
did Ukraine avoid attacking the most
modern bomber? So, so they attacked two,
um, military installations. One was, if
I recall correctly, it's been a while
now. Uh, one was a naval installation
somewhere and there was one air base in
which many Russian strategic bombers
were were damaged or destroyed. We don't
know the exact numbers. The Ukrainians
claimed 20 plus. The Russians said less.
Whatever it is, I'm not sure what kind
of bombers were destroyed. Was it the
tupole the the the tupole 160 is what?
Is it the bear? Let me just check out
very quickly. Uh or is it the swan? The
white swan. There is the bear. There's
the white swan. I think the tupole 160
would be the white swan. Right. Let me
see. Tu 160.
Is this the white swan? It is the white
swan.
Is this the white swan?
Uh, is it the white swan? Tupole 160.
Yeah, it's called the white swan. Yes.
160. And Tupolev bear.
Tupole 95. I think these are the ones.
Uh, Tupolev 95 with the counter rotating
propellers. Probably these are some of
the bombers that were damaged or and or
slash destroyed. Why did they do this
instead of that? I am not really sure. I
don't know. uh which kind of bombers
were targeted. Maybe maybe the the the
more modern ones are kept somewhere
else. Maybe you can't hit everything
that you want to, right? Uh you have
limited resources. You have limited
points of ingress into Russia. You have
limited,
you know, actors who are positioned
inside Russian territory. So you can't
hit everything you want. I mean, why
didn't they hit Moscow also, you could
ask? So they hit whatever they could and
it was definitely a pretty spectacular
operation and a significant success for
Ukraine and it was kind of a major
embarrassment for Russia not to mention
a military setback. Right? So that's the
deal. I don't really have an answer.
It's maybe they did not have the
resources in in in position to attack
the Tupal 160s. Uh Trump's latest peace
deal surrender of Ukraine to Russia. No,
it's pragmatic. Look, I'm not sure what
news you people watch. I have been
saying since February 2022 that Russia
is winning and I have been ridiculed,
right? I have been lots of people have
made fun of me that Russia is losing.
They have lost 7 million soldiers.
They've lost this. They've lost that.
Putin has cancer. Putin is dying in 3
months. All kinds of propaganda. I have
been steadfast in what I have been
saying. Russia is going to achieve its
military and political objectives in the
Ukraine conflict. Now, where are we?
This is the Trump's peace deal, right?
Is he is he actually surrendering
Ukraine to Russia? He's not surrendering
the whole of Ukraine to Russia. What
what he is proposing is that Russia gets
to keep whatever territories it has uh
captured from Ukraine
and the whole of the Luhansk Donk
Donetsk oblasts and there is a you know
a ceasefire line that will be drawn
based on more or less current locations
current you know positions on the map of
the armed forces and furthermore Ukraine
uh gives an assurance as part of Trump's
deal that it will never become a part of
NATO
and probably more.
So, is this a surrender? No, it is a
recognition of the facts on the ground.
I don't know what news sources you read
from. Maybe these are western news
sources you read from. You are observing
which is why you get the impression that
was winning all the time. And how come
Trump is surrendering everything? He's
surrendering nothing. He's simply
recognizing the realities, the ground
realities. The longer this goes on, the
more the West will be drained,
especially Europe.
It's better to freeze the conflict where
it is right now. Create a North Korea,
South Korea kind of situation. Ukraine
gets partitioned. Like I've been saying
since February 2022, Ukraine will be
partitioned. Which line? Well, if if uh
Trump's current proposal is accepted,
then the current battle lines that will
be the ceasefire line. That will be the
partition line. If uh that is not
accepted by the by by Zilinski and by
the European vas of the US, well then
maybe the the Niper River eventually
becomes the ceasefire line, which means
Russia goes for the west. Maybe there's
a regime change in Kiev, which anyway
may happen if the if Trump's um peace
deal or proposal uh goes forward, right?
So that's how I see it. It's not a
surrender. It's it's simply a
recognition of the ground realities that
Russia is winning.
The west has been propagandizing all all
over the place on social media on think
tank articles and you know BBC, CNN,
Fox, Deutsche, whatever everywhere they
have been propagandizing that Russia is
losing badly. Ukraine is winning. Yeah.
Right. So it's simply a recognition of
the ground realities.
Power says, "Why do people around the
west respect Russians? Is it really due
to the Second World War victory of
Russia? Or is there another specific
reason?"
Well, that's a good question.
The people
people around the world respect
Russians. Yeah. But people in the West,
they don't like Russia.
They many of the people in the West kind
of hate Russia. They see Russia as an
enemy, but they respect Russia. Now, do
you understand a little bit of context?
You may dislike them, but you respect
them. Now, where does respect come from?
Does it come from admiration?
Respect doesn't necessarily come from
admiration. Especially when you dislike
the nation, you dislike the nation, but
you respect them. So, it's not
admiration that's bringing out the
respect. It is fear.
At the basis of a lot of respect,
especially in geopolitics, there is
fear. Now why is Russia feared?
Because Russia won't crumble. Russia
goes after its enemies.
Russia goes after the traitors who
betray Russia. Have you heard of
pollonium?
Have you heard of the Lithuanian co case
and many other instances? Russia goes
after its traitors. Russia ensures that
justice is done. Justice to the to the
nation, justice to Rossia Matoska,
mother Russia, right? Beyond that,
Russia was in a shambles 25 years ago
and today look at Russia. It has climbed
back on its feet. It's resolute. It has
a fearsome military. It has the world's
largest nuclear arsenal. It may not have
uh the most prestigious aircraft carrier
capabilities in the world, but that
doesn't matter. It has some of the
deadliest nuclear submarines in the
world. Why is Russia Russia respected?
Because Russia doesn't take nonsense
from anyone. Yeah. And nobody can bully
Russia. That's why Russia is respected.
Russia doesn't want to play the good
boy. Please like me, sir. S please like
me.
Yeah, that's why Russia is is respected.
Now ask yourself about some other
country maybe whatever your favorite
country is, is it respected? If it is
not, then why is it not respected?
Whichever your favorite country is, ask
yourselves.
Tanmahesh Pande says, "Is Russia
becoming the most successful revisionist
power of the 21st century after its
November gains?" Uh, November gains.
which November gains. Are you talking
about Ukraine?
The lines on the map on the map in
Ukraine have been kind of frozen for a
very long time. Steady
situation, maybe a couple of miles here
and there. I'm not sure what major
November gains have happened. If
something major would have happened, I
would have known about it. I don't
register small changes
u incremental changes um or progress
in the Ukraine war. I register major
changes. So I my radar is set for major
changes major progress or regress or
whatever but little a couple of
kilometers have been caught here. Some
village was captured. I don't really
care about that. So I'm not sure what
what gains happened in November. Now is
Russia a revisionist power?
I would say a lot of Indians
they seek to regain Pakistan occupied
Kashmir. Now in some people in the west
would call it revisionism. You're trying
to change the lines of the map. You're
trying to rewrite history. Some people
in India want what? Akandharat.
That could also be ported as
revisionism. China seeks to expand its
territory.
China seeks to you know take Taiwan.
China China China seeks territory from
India. China seeks territory from
Russia. Isn't that revisionism?
So these terms like revisionism,
revisionist power etc. These are used
especially in the western media to as as
as sticks to beat nation nations with.
Um so I don't know about revisionist
power. Russia is simply looking out for
it for its best interests. And what are
Russia's best interests? You don't want
NATO on on your doorstep. So you deal
with Ukraine in the way it has to be
done and that's what it's doing. And u
how has the Ukraine campaign gone thus
far? I would say very successful, right?
The it was known that the West would
unleash sanctions on Russia and they
have. The United States, the Europeans,
every nation you could imagine, all the
vasals of the US came together and
unleashed every sanction you could
imagine on Russia and it did not have
the effect that were that they had
intended. The intention was to destroy
Russia, crush Russia's economy.
What happened? On the contrary, Russia's
economy actually grew grew to a certain
extent, right? It's not in recession.
It's actually growing. It's growing
better compared to the European
economies.
Um and Russia has not been isolated. It
has certain nations on its side. Some
are on Russia's side because of
convenience. Some are on Russia's side
because of other reasons, whatever it
is. Right? So, Russia has been
successful thus far in the Ukraine
conflict. And the way things are going,
uh, it looks like, uh, Trump will sooner
or later insist and prevail upon Ukraine
to accept a ceasefire proposal, which
has to be in Russia's favor because
Russia has the facts on the ground.
Russia has created facts on the ground
and those you can create, you can draw a
map whichever way you want, but you know
what's there on the ground, right? So
you have to recognize that
and uh yeah so Russia is going to
prevail in the Ukraine conflict. Uh so
it's it's going to be successful. Now is
it going to be the is it is is it
becoming the most successful revisionist
power? I don't know. The 21st century uh
it's another 75 years years to go. Thus
far Russia is doing a good deal of
standing up to the to the west and we
are witnessing the the the emergence of
cold war 2.0 zero uh which most likely
will drag India into it as well and it
remains to be seen on which side India
goes.
Minimalist Maverick says it seems like
Russia is going allin in this war and
the West won't supply it won't stop
supplying arms to Ukraine timeline wise
if it drags till 2035.
See, Russia,
there's this question that pops up all
the time, doesn't it? Why is Russia
playing the slow game [clears throat] in
the Ukraine war? Why is it dragging out
the conflict for years? Why is it happy
with this frozen war scenario?
Why is it happy with this slow war
scenario? You know, frozen battle lines,
stagnant battle lines. Why doesn't it
simply make a move on move on K and
finish it off? Right?
So that's one question that keeps
popping up. But we know that Russia has
the military capabilities required to do
that. They can flatten Ukraine tomorrow
morning if they want to. But clearly
they don't want to. And why do they not
want to? First of all, they don't see
the Ukrainians as foreign to them. They
see the Ukrainians as their kin Slavic
people. And secondly, the longer this
war drags on. See, if you end the war
tomorrow, you take Kiev, you dethrone
Zilinsky, send him into exile hopefully,
[laughter] whatever, and you partition
Ukraine at at a certain line. When the
war ends, and then if the war ends, what
happens? The West has to stop supplying
weapons, arms, ammunition, money, funds,
whatever to Ukraine because Ukraine no
longer exists.
So the financial drain on the West ends.
But if the war goes on and the West
keeps on investing money and arms,
ammunition, whatever the Ukraans need.
So it keeps on bleeding the West. But
you could argue it's also bleeding
Russia. But you see, Russia is an
otarchy. And this war has actually
strengthened Russia's industrial base,
military base, economic base. It's had a
very counterintuitive effect on Russia.
It has strengthened Russia. Russia is
now a full-fledged war economy and they
are robust now in Russia you know if you
look at historically how Russia has
performed in wars initially in any war
they don't perform well but give it a
couple of years and then see them
rebound right initially they don't do
well but then they adapt they adapt and
they have the territory and they have
the resources and they have whatever
else is needed so Russia has adapted and
Russia is doing well
So um
so the war will go on as long as it is
beneficial to Russia and that's why
Trump wants to end it soon right so that
it's the the so it's stops being such a
such a drain on the west uh so how do I
see this going I I I
would say that the war will most likely
end in some kind of ceasefire maybe in
the next 6 to 12 months
Trump will ensure it happens because see
first of all it's a matter of prestige
for Trump also. He had promised his
voters that he will end the Ukraine war
on day one of his presidency and this
has not happened. It makes him look very
bad. Trump doesn't like looking bad. So,
he's going to make it happen. And if
Zalinsky and the Europeans insist on
keeping the war going on, then he will
do something about it. Right? So, I the
way I see it, the war should end in the
next 6 to 12 months. It will end in some
kind of ceasefire in some kind of
ceasefire deal which will not be good
for Ukraine but it will recognize the
realities on the ground and until the
war ends the west has no option but to
keep supplying arms, weapons, fuel, food
supplies, humanitarian supplies, pilot
fighter planes, whatever it fuel etc to
Ukraine and that's a big drain on the
western economy on the European economy.
So I think it will end sooner rather
than later.
ICMBBS
says it seems the prime minister heard
my critique about the education system
that keeps us in inferiority complex.
How would you go about changing it? Uh
the prime minister has heard my
critique.
I recall
seeing some statement or hearing about
some statement from the prime minister
about the macau and education system or
something. Uh it's good to hear that but
what action is being taken is the
question.
I have been speaking about this five,
six, I don't know how many years as as
as long as I have been a face in the
public domain. I have been speaking
about the mccllin education system how
it needs the colonial education system.
It needs to be reformed. I have at least
like I think three episodes of the ask
show dated to the education system and
the need to reform the education system
and I have not only
pointed out the problems which anybody
can, I have also given solutions which
very few people do.
I've given very specific situations u
solutions. Are any of those solutions
being implemented is the question I
would like to ask. There is something
called the new education policy. The new
education policy doesn't address any of
the
any of the fundamental defects issues in
the in the education system. You can
revise some of the syllabus.
You can you know restructure the
education system in in some in some
ways. That's a good start but that's a
minor minor change.
The deeper malaise still remains
right. So how would I go about changing
the education system? Once again let me
show you all how I would do that. Uh I
will not explain it in detail right now
but I will tell you where to look for my
explanation about how to change the
education system because I have spoken
about this in great detail. So uh let me
put that on the screen. One second. Give
me a second. So you can check out those
episodes in which I have spoken about
this in great detail. Give me a second.
All right. So this is my channel. These
are the this is the live stream tab over
here. As you can see it was about
episode 28 29. See? Okay. So I have
three episodes. Episode 28 of Askabit
episode 30 and episode 31. In these
three episodes, I have spoken in great
detail about how the education system is
a disaster for India. How it is it is
keeping India down. It is ruining the
ruining the future of of the future
generations of India of Indians. And
what needs to be done to fix this?
Episodes 28,
30 and 31 of the Ask Bijit Show. The
same show that you are watching right
now. This was about more than four years
ago that I spoke about it. And whatever
I spoke about, whatever I said in those
episodes, it still is 100% relevant
today. So that's how I would go about
changing it. If you are interested,
please watch those episodes. Thank you,
sir. Thank you, ma'am.
Okay.
Uh WBR464
says, "Did you know Yvani Pojan was a
Jew?" I did not know that. I'm not
aware. Was he a Jew? If he was a Jew,
well, okay. Zalinski is also a Jew.
There are plenty of Jewish people who
are in prominent positions in the west.
It is what it is. Yeah. So I was not
aware that he's a Jew. If you would like
to if you would like me to fact check
that I can do that. But um not sure how
it is relevant. Yi
noi.
Oh, was he Jewish? This fine gentleman.
Let's see.
Open up.
Open up. All right, let us see.
Father was etc.
His father and stepfather are believed
to be of Jewish descent. So, it's
believed to be. We don't know for sure.
And it how does it really matter? It's
all right. Okay.
Andy Bud says, "Big fan." Thank you very
much, Andy G. Please throw some light on
the recent G20 summit. Did Mr. Modi go
do good by visiting it? I hope Donald
Trump is not angry tariff threat. I
haven't examined the G20 summit. See,
um just FYI to everybody, I don't I'm
not a news surfer. I the way I examine
the world, analyze the world is I do it
not in real time. I take my time. If
something happens, I'll wait for a week
for it to for the thing to happen. Let's
say there's a summit, a major summit
happening somewhere. I will not be stuck
to the television screen watching the
latest news updates about what's
happening. I'll take my time. I'll wait
for a week for the summit after the
summit is done and then I will examine
what are the major outcomes of the
summit. So the summit has just happened.
I would say is it still on? I'm not sure
about that. So I'm not even sure if it's
on or not. And I know that Prime
Minister Modi attended the summit
obviously and it was in South Africa if
I recall. I mean the images of Prime
Minister Modi's visit were all over
social media. I mean even today I saw
some of them. So it looks like it was it
is still ongoing or maybe it's just
over. I'm not sure. I'll take a week or
so to analyze what happened in the
summit, what came out of it, what was
its relevance for India and then we can
discuss it. Um right now it's it's too
early for me to comment. Okay. But I
will certainly uh revisit this this
matter let's say in a week's time.
But uh did Mr. Modi do a good thing by
visiting by attending the G20 summit?
Well, yes, India should attend these
summits. We hosted the G20 right in 2023
just a couple of years ago. Um and one
of the major things we did in the 2023
summit was to make the African Union a
member of the G20.
So yeah, nobody had bothered bo bo bo bo
bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo bo
bo bo bo bothered to do that until we
did it. Uh so yeah it is important for
India to be present in these summits and
participate and take a leadership role
wherever applicable relevant and
possible and uh yeah so it's a good
thing that Mr. Modi did attend the
summit and participate in it. I'm not
sure about Donald Trump whether he's
angry or not. Tariff threats yeah well
tariffs are on right and there's a 500%
tariff threat also that there is
somewhere down the corner. We'll see
about that. Minimalist Maverick says,
"Explain African and Latin American
geopolitics and who is whose v was and
business opportunities. If possible, can
you make a six-hour video on this?"
Well, you gave me the sol you first gave
me the problem and they then gave me the
solution. See, if you want me to explain
African and Latin American geopolitics,
it will take me six hours. Africa is the
largest continent. Latin America, South
America is a gi gigantic subcont
gigantic continent and to understand
geopolitics and to understand history.
Now it's impossible for me to explain in
the next 5 minutes even 15 minutes the
history
the context of just let's say African
geopolitics because there are so many
factors so many players involved when I
just now the first question I took was
about the conflict in Sudan right the
civil war in Sudan that took me like 10
15 minutes to answer and even for that I
gave a very high level overview of
what's been happening in Sudan so you
see it's it will probably take me a
six-hour video to explain all of that in
detail.
But if I were to explain about the
vasalhood situation,
there is no major power in Africa.
They're all somebody or the other's
vasals. There is again same way there is
no major geopolitical power in South
America, even Central America. They are
all somebody's vasals either directly or
indirectly. Who is that somebody? Well,
it's definitely not Russia or China. The
Chinese are kind of involved in Africa.
Definitely. Even the Russians are the
Chinese are the money, the Russians are
the muscles are the muscle. You have the
Vagner group and then you have the
evolution of the Vagner group. But
whatever it is, it's the same entity or
maybe a slightly evolved or modified
entity whatever. So you have Russia and
China involved in Africa geopolitically
because uh they've got to be present
there. Africa is so rich in resources
and why would they not want to partake
of that? Similarly in South America also
the Chinese have been uh a a decent not
a decent robust player actually the past
15 or so years and yeah but overall if
you look at Latin America it is under
you could say the domination the
hedgemony of the United States. The good
old Monro doctrine of the 19th century
still applies. It is no longer
fashionable to call it the Monro
Doctrine because it sounds outdated but
it is what it is. it still applies. And
in Africa, well, the French were a major
power for quite some time, but now they
have completely withdrawn and they have
created a power vacuum which the
Russians will be happy to exploit, even
the Chinese,
but mainly the major major power in the
in the in the continent of Africa is
still the United States.
Okay. Ritik P says, "Why did Trump skip
the G20 summit? Is G2 a new world order?
Now, I am not sure why Trump skipped the
G20 summit. I like I said a while ago,
uh I have not I I'll take my time to
analyze what happened in the G20 summit.
I don't surf the news in in real time
because you see why you may wonder why
do I not keep track of what's happening
in real time? I mean, if I am supposedly
a geopolitical analyst or whatever, then
should I not be staying in touch with
what's happening in the world? Should I
not be interested in what's happening
right now? Isn't it important? Right?
You see, the the the truth is
that the more you watch the news, the
less you know about what's happening in
the world.
99% of of the news is noise.
It's shouting. It's propaganda.
It's agenda setting. It's narrative
setting. The more you spend your time
watching the news, the less you will
understand what's happening. So I don't
watch the news. I take my time and then
I I have my sources of where to obtain
my information from and then I analyze
it calmly. Right? So I'm not a news
surfer. I'm going to take my time and
I'm not quite sure what Trump has
decided about the G20. Did he skip it?
In case he skipped it, why did he skip
it? I I I'll look into that. Is G2 a new
world order right now?
Not quite.
Um it's still too early for a G2
situation. It's more like a G4 G5
situation. Who are the G4 G5? So you
obviously have the US and China, the two
two major economies, but China is not a
superpower. Even if the US is trying to
position China as kind of a peer rival,
peer competitor, China is nothing
compared to the US, especially in terms
of military capabilities and power
projection capabilities. Economically,
it's kind of reaching there, right? So,
you have the US and China. These are G1
and G2, the two. Then you have Russia, a
major military power, right? The most
powerful nuclear power in the world. So,
that's G3. There you have it. Then you
have the fourth largest economy in the
world soon to be the third largest
economy India which is also a major at
least a regional power right it's one of
the great powers in the world that's
India despite all of its problems India
is still there a major power and it's a
it's a growing power I would not say a
rising power I would say growing power
it's growing India is going to grow at 6
7% a year hopefully maybe I would like
10% but let's see so India is there then
you have the European Union which is not
really a major player anymore Europe is
going to be back quarter of the world in
the 21st century but still it still
appears. So it's like a G4 G5 situation
right now and the US doesn't want that.
They would like a G2 situation. The US
doesn't want multipolarity. They want
bipolarity but it's too early to say
that G2 is a thing now even though Trump
would like it that way.
Basar Bandit says land border between
China and Russia is pretty large. Well
yes pretty large indeed. Then what is so
special about the Usuri River area that
China chose to occupy it recognize it as
their own in current maps and in
history? Well, you see you have to if
you want to understand this I have to
tell you a story
and and what does a story mean in the
context of geopolitics I would discuss
history here.
So you see okay let's look at the map
obviously to understand what we are
discussing here we have to see the map.
So let us pull out the map of the world.
Where is it? Here it is. So first of
all, Russia and China. Do they have a
border? Yes sir. Yes ma'am. So you see
there's this border here.
This border which is what about 50 km
wide? [laughter]
See here. Oh it's not even 50 km in a
straight line. It's about 39 km. But if
you if you do the contours and all that
if you do a contour integral it may be
about 50 km. So on the one side on the
left on the west you have the great
nation of Kazakhstan
on the east you have Mongolia south you
have Chinese occupied whatever East
Turkiststan and in the north you have
Russia 50 km there then you have
Mongolia and you go further east and
then you have the major Russia China
border that is very very significant all
right starting from here all the way
north of Manuria
and all the way to the north Korea
border. So south of Ladivosto you have a
triunction of Russia, China and North
Korea.
Okay, Russia, China and North Korea.
Where is North Korea? Where is it?
Um I'm Yeah. So it's it's a trijunction.
Russia, China, North Korea. Let me zoom
in. This is indeed North Korea, isn't
it?
All right. North Korea. Yes. So that is
the deal. So it's a pretty long border.
Now historically in the 19 what 19 1969
Russia and China nearly went to war the
Usuri River clashes the Usuri River
dispute and there was this island the
Chinese call it the Jenbao island or
whatever it is. It's somewhere here.
Which island is it? It will be a little
difficult for me to pinpoint the exact
location of the island. Uh it will be
somewhere in this area. Is it this one?
Let me see if I can find it. Jinpa.
Jinbao Island. Zoom in. There we have
it. So, you can see now it's on the
Chinese side of the border. But there
was a time when the border ran across
the island and this was disputed by both
nations and the two nations nearly went
to war. There were major military
clashes over here. Hundreds of soldiers
died and the Russians had decided to
nuke China. But the Americans came and
rescued China and that's how things
went. So now what's the deal? Uh what is
special about the Usuri River region and
why does China seek this? So once again
we go to the map. So you see if you look
at Russia's far east it is enormous as
you can see but Russia was based out of
what? Well, if you look at the origin of
the Roose people, their original capital
going back about a thousand years was
Kiev. It's now called Kiev. For some
reason, it was Kiev. They were called
the Kievan Roose. And later, the capital
became Moscow, Moscowi. And for a couple
of centuries, the the roose were under
the Mongol yoke for a couple of
centuries. And eventually the the duchi
or duki of Moscowi became a big thing.
And eventually um Russia became an
empire and then Russia started expanding
eastwards eastwards eastwards and all
these territories these were tungus
peoples who used to live here Mongolic
people I mean north of Mongolia you have
a big region which was historically also
Mongolia which is now part of Russia. So
the Russians the roose they expanded
eastwards gradually and what did they
seek they sought fur fur trading in the
frozen wastelands of northern Eurasia.
Nobody else wanted to go there. So the
roose went there and they traded in
first and they slowly annexed all these
territories. Now the Chinese claimed
many of the territories which are now
currently part of Russia and the in the
1850s the Chinese are fighting major
revolts.
The Dungan revolt uh uh and the the East
Turkiststan revolt etc. the Hui revolt.
So they were fighting major major
revolts in territories that they claimed
as their own in the west in the west of
what is today China. And you also had
the gunboat diplomacy the opium wars
that was going on the west was bullying
China the Chinese century of
humiliation. So during this time the
Russians took territory from China as
part of treaties that [clears throat]
they signed with the Chinese. So the the
Russians through legal means took
territory from the Chinese major
territory which is now part of the
Russian far east. But the Chinese was
always historic has seen that as a
historical injustice and they seek those
territories back. But the Chinese say
that the whole of Eurasia is ours
essentially.
So that's the deal. So looks like the
Usuri River thing was you know one of
the points of the dispute. the the
Chinese claim way more territory than
what is on the map right now. So the
Chinese claim Ladi was they claim they
claimed many other parts of the Russian
Far East and it's going to be an issue
between Russia and China sooner or
later. Right? So that's kind of the
history. If you see that in the in in
the historical context then you will
understand that there's a lot that's
happened in this region. The Chinese
have claims the Russians actually have
you know facts on the ground.
The Chinese are revisionists.
They say that you know we had way more
territory and we want it back
eventually. That is the deal.
Aries manticor says a small suggestion.
You can try to host live streams on kick
as well. I am live streaming on kick
right now. This live streaming that you
may be watching on YouTube. It is also
simultaneously being live streamed to
kick to Twitch to X or Twitter. it's
being live streamed to LinkedIn and I
sometimes live stream to Facebook also
at the same time. So I'm live streaming
to multiple destinations at the same
time. Um yeah so it's a good suggestion
and I am grateful for you that you have
suggested this. I'm doing that and many
creators have been shadow locked on
YouTube is an alternative with a much
younger crowd. Keep going. Thank you
very much. Yes, I know. I'm not I'm not
sure about many creators. If this has
happened to other creators also on
YouTube, but as you know, my channel is
there's an upper limit input to my
channel. It will not reach 950 for the
foreseeable future. Right? Somebody in
YouTube is not a big fan of me. Probably
some fine gentleman or fine lady in
YouTube India. Somebody maybe I should
do something about it. We'll see about
that. That's okay. It doesn't matter.
Right. Next. finding myself shrishi kota
says as a local from siliguri I'm seeing
rapid development new industries bigger
highways more air activity given the
current geopolitical situation how will
the state of siliguri be in the next 10
years so you're asking me to make a
future prediction I don't really make
future predictions I can but let's let's
understand what we are discussing here
we'll talk about siliguri
so excuse me when we talk When we
discuss Siliguri, we discussing this
what is called the Siliguri corridor. So
there is this city over here called
Siliguri. It's part of West Bengal. Even
Dhargiling is part of West Bengal. And
north of that we have Sikkim obviously.
So Siliguri is is part of West Bengal.
And to the east you have the great state
of Assam.
So we have the Siliguri corridor which
is roughly 30 kilometers wide. 22 km 23
km wide. Well well well yeah which
connects the Indian far east to what
they call the Indian mainland right and
for some reason our fantastic leaders of
the past they decided that we will
accept this sort of map with this
so-called chicken's leg neck that
connects our far east with the rest of
the nation. So in Siliguri uh as Shishi
says she is seeing rapid development,
new industries, bigger highways, better
highways, more air activity.
So what so I'm glad to hear that first
of all. Yeah. And obviously Siliguri is
a very important uh uh sector you know
location for India. It's very important
that we have robust infrastructure in
the Siliguri region. No, because see uh
it is not it is obviously something that
borders the nation of Bangladesh and it
is also not far from Chinese occupied
Tibet and it it also borders with Nepal.
So it's an it's a it's a region that is
kind of international if you want to
consider Bangladesh and Nepal
international it is what it is right and
Bangladesh obviously is not was
historically East Pakistan it has once
again transformed into kind of like East
Pakistan it's not a very friendly nation
right now it's a newly minted US vasal
state and kind of hostile towards India
so there is that also
so
that's the current geopolitical
situation right that's the current
geopolitical situation. Even Nepal has
had a regime change very recently, a
so-called Gen Z uh regime change,
revolution, whatever you want to call
it. And yeah, there is the question of
what kind of government is in Nepal
also. So given this situation, what will
be the state of Siliguri in the next 10
years? I would say that Siliguri should
be in a better state in the next 10
years. One of the one of the things I've
heard is that there's the there's a
significant infiltration of
Bangladeshes, illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators in the region. That's what
I've heard apocryphily. I'm not sure if
it is entirely correct. I've heard there
is a big
number of Bangladeshi infiltrators who
have settled in the region. I am not
sure if it's true. I hope it is not
true. But that is something that the
government needs to do something about.
I would say urgently as as is the case
of the rest of the country, the
Bangladeshi infiltrators, the illegals
need to be uh repatriated to Bangladesh
at the earliest. Um
so hopefully that is done if the
situation is indeed the case that like I
said and I would say that you know we
need fortification of of railways,
highways, all of that in the region.
What else could happen in the next 10
years? Well, the ideal situation is that
the Siliguri corridor is widened and you
know Rangapur etc returns to India. That
would be the ideal situation. If uh the
nation of East Pakistan you know
persists with its anti-India
stance and if they give us an
opportunity then if the opportunity
presents itself we should uh take back
the Rangapur region Dingapur Rangapur
etc and uh you know reintegrate it with
the motherland. Uh so that is something
that could potentially happen in the
next 10 years. Beyond that uh it is well
hard to say. Yeah. But oh I'm hopeful
that uh the situation in Sidiguri
improves even more compared to what we
are seeing right now.
King Rituik says in the 1970s India was
weak, India was poor. We needed the help
of the USSR/Russia to defend ourselves
from the US and Pakistan. Still then how
could the USSR not vasalize India? They
saved us. Does that make Mrs. Gandhi
better than Mr. Nehu?
So the question is
was India a vasal state of the USSR in
the 20th century? India was definitely
an ally
of the USSR.
India proclaimed itself to be
non-aligned
and India did
do certain things that were not in line
with the USSR's interests. For example,
when the USSR invaded Afghanistan on
December 25, 1979, India opposed that,
right? But overall, India was aligned
with the USSR.
So you could say that India and the USSR
were aligned despite India's
posturing as being you know that it it
was a non-aligned nation. India was very
much on the side of the USSR
and yeah India was weak, India was poor
because of the economic model our
fantastic leaders had adopted Fabian
socialism. Yeah. So that was the case
and Pakistan was in was in better shape
than us. um their economy was doing
better than than ours until the the late
1980s, even the early 1990s, right? And
the Pakistanis had aligned with the
United States. They cho chose the
winning side. We chose the side that
would eventually lose the cold war and
we had to
rely on the USSR to for support
especially in 1971, right? And so we
know we know the situation
now. Now, did the USSR vaselize India?
Not quite. How do I say why do I say
India was not vaselized? Because the
USSR did not control India's foreign
policy. The USSR did not control India's
economic policy. When you vaselize the
nation, you control their economic and
foreign policies and you leave them to
deal with their internal situation. That
you take care of, but you have to say do
what we say about your economic and
foreign policy and military policy. So,
that was not the case. That's why the
USSR did not vaselize India. Why did the
USSR not vaselize India? I would say
that they they not did not see the need
to do that. There were other nations
that were aligned with the USSR in in a
variety of similar ways and the USSR did
not seek to vilize that. Was it a good
thing? Was it a bad thing? I think it
was something that was bad for the USA.
If if they had adopted the American
policy of vasalizing other nations by
insisting that they control those
nations economic and and and and foreign
and military policies like they did with
Pakistan and other nations, then the
USSR would have had way more power
projection capabilities. But for
whatever reason, they chose not to do
that. And that's why it was good for us,
of course. Yeah. That we were not
vasals. Uh it is alleged that the USSR
had you could say allegedly bought out
certain politicians in India allegedly
whoever they were but overall India was
not a vasal. So the USSR did not seek to
vasalize India. They sought to have
India aligned with them ideologically
and geopolitically which we were. So
does that make Mrs. Gandhi better than
Mr. Nu? Look overall Mrs. Gandhi was a
far better leader than than her father
Mr. Nu. There's no question about that.
No question about that. Overall,
she was
Aries Manticor says, "Should we focus on
on creating multi-terrain AI drone
swarms in instead of jets and
submarines? Cheaper, faster, and more
potent with our missile technology?" I
would say very much so. Yes.
Right. But for that we need highquality
indigenous AI systems.
Does India have a single homegrown
highquality AI system?
Does India have even one of those?
I haven't seen any. Maybe I'm wrong and
if if I'm wrong then I'll be happy about
that. But India whether it is the
private sector or the public sector
whether it's the government of India
whether it's any IIT or whatever or or
some private sector company does has
anybody developed a high quality AI
model similar to the quality that you
have of AI models that you have coming
out of the United States and China
do we have anything similar we don't
right we don't so to create these drone
swarms that that are AI enabled AI
equipped you need high quality AI first
of all
uh you can have some autonomy etc that
is not really see for example during
operation sindur we had these ancient
anti-aircraft guns that were not quite
AI equipped but they they had been made
kind of autonomous right they and they
they were able to take out all the
Pakistani drones and and whatever else
whatever else the Pakistanis lobbed at
us so that's not quite AI but it's kind
of it was kind autonomous. It was these
were self automatically targeting
weapons. So you take a 1950s weapon and
add some layers of software to it and it
becomes a tremendously potent thing. So
India is very good at doing these
things. Now imagine if India has its own
AI systems. Imagine what India will do
then. So we should do that. I I 100%
agree. So you develop military AI
systems
that can control swarms of drones. Let's
say you have a drone that costs 10,000
rupees. Get a thousand of those like a
drone of like a swarm of mosquitoes. And
then you unleash them and they all talk
to each other. They know exactly what
the others are doing in real time in
space and time and they connect with the
satellite or whatever to the home base.
and the home base you have AI and even
on the drones you have AI chips and then
you can go and unleash mayhem you can
take out aircraft carriers with that if
you want to right just these flying
drones now imagine if you have
undersea drones or even
even surface you know surface of the
ocean drones
so the Ukrainians had uh they had
attacked the Kirch bridge bridge a
couple of times The bridge that connects
Crimea with mainland Russia. They had
one of the attacks was by was was done
with these autonomous boats that were
either remote control or autonomously
targeted whatever it was and it was able
to damage the bridge. So [snorts]
imagine you have small boats which have
explosives and they know what to do, how
to bypass defenses and whatnot. Then
imagine what those can do. You can also
have undersea vehicles, robotic
submarines, small ones that may look
like a large fish or or that may be the
size of a large fish, but that can
unleash mayhem because of its explosive
uh payloads.
And how do you control those? Well,
different technologies. So, my point is
yes, we should do that. We very much
should do that. Then eventually all of
this will replace jets and submarines.
Maybe not submarines, maybe not long
rangers. See, I'll tell you what's the
difference and where AI drone swarms and
these things will not be able to do
certain roles.
When you have fighter planes,
some of the fighter planes have very
long ranges. When you have strategic
bombers, they have ranges of thousands
of kilometers. Can a drone fly, let's
say, 1,000 km? Most likely not. Drones
have batteries, right? lithium ion
battery, sodium and what whatever
technology of battery you use but it's
going to have a limited charge which
means it will have a limited range. So
you can't have you can only so drones
can only be used for tactical
um purposes tactical warfare. You can't
use them for strategic purposes which is
long range stuff. So that's one of the
limitations of drones. But I'm sure
technology will eventually be able to
overcome those uh limitations as well.
But yes, India should focus on
indigenous AI, highquality AI. India
should focus on quantum computing very
important. And India should focus on
drone warfare and we kind of are but
imagine we if we have our own AI system
and then we integrate that with our
drone swarms. Imagine that. Yeah, we
should do that for sure.
Basar Bandit says a pattern as to how
dictators who get funded from the west
to create havoc in their own country or
other countries later get taken care of.
Saddam Hussein, Palahi, Zial Hak, Anar
Sadat because they go rogue or why?
Okay.
So when we talk about Muhammad Razavvi,
he was
US obviously he was a US asset
um who was ruling Persia and uh see so
Palvi had ousted Muhammad Musader.
Muhammad Musadev had nationalized Iran's
oil industry. He had ejected the
British, British petroleum or British
oil, whatever it was called, from Persia
and that made the West very sad,
very sad. It was such a heartbreaking
thing for the United States and for the
West, which is why Muhammad Mosad was
ousted and Muhammad Pahvi took over and
he once again opened the doors to the
west and allowed the West to siphon off
Porschia's oil.
So, Pahvi was eventually ousted in 1979.
He was not taken care of by the West. He
was taken care of by the by the by the
regime of the moolas, the moolas, by
Kmeni, right? So, Baklavi was not taken
care of. You could, you know, he was not
ousted by the United States or the West.
It was an indigenous kind of thing you
could say. But when it comes to Saddam
Hussein, he was a US asset, wasn't he?
The United States used Saddam Hussein as
a stick to beat Iran with because Iran
had ousted their vasal, their puppet,
Balawi. So the US armed Saddam Hussein's
Iraq and induced Iraq and to go to war
with Iran. That's the Iran Iraq war of
the 1980s. A ruinous war that ruined
both nations. And eventually what was
the outcome? Nothing. Nothing. it was
just ruin us and it it it ruined both
nations especially Persia especially
Iran. So the United States used Saddam
Hussein for that specific purpose and
then they disposed of him. They gave him
the go ahead to invade Kuwait in 1990
1990 or wherever it was and then they
said why did you do this? You are evil.
We're going to smash you now. That's
what they did to Sadda. Zial Hak was
funded by the US. Um in the aftermath of
the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, the
Americans funded um
the Pakistani is the Pakistani military
and uh taught them how to use what we
now called terror, now we call
terrorism, the mujahedin to fight the
Soviets in Afghanistan. And once that
ended the Mjahedin were rerouted into
India into Kashmir. In the 1980s the
Pakistanis were were uh playing uh havoc
in Punjab Indian Punjab also right. So
all of that was funded by the US. So
Saddam, so Zulhak was the Pakistani
dictator of the time and then Zia Hak
goes he takes a he goes on a airplane
with the US ambassador uh Arnold Raffle
and there's a crate of mangoes on the
plane and the crate of mangoes explodes
exploding a case of exploding mangoes
and Ziaak dies. So the US decided that
it's enough of Xiaawhak and we'll have
somebody else most likely and it looks
like their own ambassador was made
collateral damage. An unwaral sad
different story. So the question is is
there a patent to this? There is
obviously a patent to this. So the US
has historically been very fond of
dictators. They preach democracy and
human rights to the world. But if you
look at the number of regime changes
they've done in Africa and other
countries, you will see they always
install dictators in these countries
because dictators are easy to deal with.
Democracy is a messy thing. You can't
predict the outcome of what's going to
happen in the country in the next 5
years. An election can change
everything. Then you have to cultivate
new assets. Why do that? Invest in
dictators. So the US preaches democracy
to the world, but they invest in
dictators in various nations across the
world. They've done so many regime
change operations in Africa, in the 20th
century, in other parts of Asia, so much
more. So there's a pattern and
eventually if a dictator becomes too big
for its for his boots if he starts not
if he shows a tendency to now no longer
cooperate with the US
or be obstinate in certain demands you
can always get rid of him right and have
somebody else uh take over the country
so there's a pattern no question about
that if you look at Africa there are
plenty of places where you have
dictators who
have been installed
Yeah. And many of them and some of them
are going doing a really good job
actually. Uh I shall not take names of
countries.
Peel strong man says your favorite
geopolitical joke. Joke apart from
Stalin Sri Lanka. Favorite geopolitical
joke. That's
that's a googly like they say. Googly.
Is it is it a flipper? Flipper.
I can't think of a geopolitical joke
right now.
Let me think about it. If I can recall
something, I'll I'll let you know. I
can't think of a geopolitical joke right
now. Shubam Var says Christopher
Columbus was Jewish, searched for India
the day after the Spanish expelled Jews.
Is it true? Was the internal politics in
the Marata Empire? Why we lost to Brits?
We are discussing sir Shubam G. This if
you look at the title of this episode,
it is geopolitics episode. We are not
discussing history today sir. If I start
discussing history now, if I start
discussing science, then the people who
have come to
see me speak about geopolitics, they
will be very disappointed. I have made a
promise in the title of the episode,
geopolitics. I shall not break my
promise, sir. It is bad form to break
your promises. You have to keep your
word if you are an honorable person. So,
I shall stick to geopolitics today and
we can discuss history in a history
episode. All right. Thank you, sir.
Hindutwa rises says do you foresee a
pahelgam type attack in the next month
considering the deep state's attack
attempt to dismantle the ruling party
have failed.
I will not talk about next month. How
will I know? See understand this. If you
want to if you want me to say whether
something is will happen next week or
next month or 78 days from now then you
are presupposing that I have some very
specific information
right. I can give you an answer to this
question only if I have very specific
information
that points in that direction. Now I am
simply
a person who observes the world who has
some understanding of how the world
operates and works. I have some
understanding of the patterns and cycles
of history which translate into
geopolitics and that's the basis on
which I speak about things. I don't have
access to classified information to
privileged information.
I don't have access to information from
security agencies or intelligence
agencies and that's why I cannot answer
a question about whether I can uh
whether I foresee something happening
next month. What I can tell you
is that the likelihood of pahelam time
pahelgam type attacks
in the next 6 to 12 months is higher
compared to pre pelgam or pre- pulwama
palgam pre- palgam
see the Pakistanis see understand this
we have let's discuss three nations
China, India, Pakistan.
China is about roughly four times more
powerful than India.
And India is let's see I don't know
[clears throat] about 10 times more
powerful than Pakistan maybe 15 maybe 20
times more powerful than Pakistan.
So there's a huge gulf between India and
Pakistan and also between China and
India. So when it comes to India and
China,
knowing that China is four times more
powerful than us, we don't poke the
Chinese
right, we don't do things that will
irritate the Chinese, annoy the Chinese,
bleed the Chinese. We don't do a thing
like that. But when it comes to Pakistan
and India, the Pakistanis, despite being
so much less powerful than India, they
keep on poking, proddding, and trying to
bleed India. That's been their strategy
from day one, right? From 1947 onwards.
That's always been their strategy. So
they will continue that. But they will
seek to
continue it continue this this strategy
of poking, proddding and bleeding India
and conducting terrorist activities if
possible in India while keeping it below
a certain threshold. What is the
threshold? the threshold that that will
lead to war because see the government's
the Indian government's new new policy
new doctrine whatever you want to call
it is that a terrorist attack is going
to be se seen as an act of war
but what kind of terrorist attack
it's going to it's going to have to be a
major terrorist attack so how many
people died in the pahelam attack I
would I would say more than 20 right
something similar to that so maybe the
Pakistanis
will continue their [snorts] horrific
evil policy of terrorism but they'll
keep it below a certain threshold
perhaps.
Yeah. So that could happen
that there is a high possibility of that
continuing to happen. Maybe they will
instead of conducting crossber terrorism
maybe they will uh
maybe they will support various
individuals let's say who may be Indian
citizens like those alleged not alleged
they're not alleged doctors they're real
doctors right those doctors who were
recently apprehended
they were all Indian citizens right so
if they do terrorism in India can we
blame Pakistan for that can't really
blame Pakistan for So that's the kind of
things they will do. Um but yes there is
a higher probability of this sort of
thing happening in the next 6 to 12
months. I can't say about next month.
The reborn sonatani says do you see
Canada coming out of the job housing
rapidly incre increasing inflation
medical system immigration crisis
anytime soon or that won't happen as
long as it keeps playing second fiddle
to the US. Look, Canada is destined to
play second fiddle to the US as long as
Canada exists.
Understand
that the United States, it allows the
existence of Canada.
Why does it allow the existence of
Canada? Because Canada is nothing but an
extension of the US.
It is a vasal state.
The US doesn't need to occupy Canada or
send the military to Canada because
Canada is harmless and Canada's
external policy, economic policy, it all
serves US interests.
Right? And Canada doesn't have any
leaders. They have not allowed any real
leaders to emerge in Canada. Do you see
any leader who can take Canada in a new
direction? Do you see any such person on
the horizon? You only see mediocrities
puppets.
Puppets like Justin Trudeau Justin
Trudeau. What a loser of a politician he
is.
Absolutely zero leadership quality.
That sort of person. Now you have this
gentleman called Carne who has been
tasked with taking Canada in a slightly
different direction.
But to solve all the major problems, the
job crisis, the housing crisis,
inflation,
medical system, immigration.
See, immigration can be solved like
that,
like that. Just change the policy and
enforce it, right? But they won't do it.
And anyway, Canada is a nation of
immigrants. If you disregard the
indigenous people who are second-ass
citizens, right? Canada is is a nation
of immigrants but they want to keep so
you can't really do that also but yeah
you can if if it's up to you
so the situation in Canada it's uh in my
opinion not going to change
significantly and Canada as long as it
exists will play second fiddle to the US
it simply cannot break out of the US
orbit the moment it goes against the US
the moment it tries to decouple its
decision-m process from the US interests
there's going to be a tremendous
repercussion set of repercussions for
whoever is the leader who has decided to
change course won't happen Canada is
completely at the service of the US and
that's how it is going to continue so I
don't see any major changes happening in
Canada if there is an immigration crisis
well the roots of the immigration crisis
don't lie in Canada they lie further
south and whatever else also yeah
essentially you have a bunch of
extremely mediocre politicians who are
doing a terrible job
and for some reason your people
Canadians keep voting for them. So, and
I haven't even discussed the Kalistthan
the support for the Kalistthani
separatists who are actually Canadian
citizens, right? All all that nonsense.
Sangam Kumar says, "Is the US sniffing
war in the Indo-Pacific so ended a war?"
The US still hasn't ended the the
Ukraine war. They seek to end it soon.
They seek to Trump wants a ceasefire
now. I mean, he's he's been angling for
a ceasefire from the day he became
president for the second time. but it's
not really worked out for him. But he is
desperate to end the Ukraine war. He
wants a ceasefire.
Does he seek a ceasefire because they
want a war in the Indo-Pacific region?
Well, I would say there's a high
likelihood of war between India and
Pakistan in the next 2 three years. Um
much more major war than the last one.
The three-day war, Operation Zindur.
There was a limited war, wasn't it? It
wasn't a full-scale war because the
infantries um you know the ground forces
weren't involved. It was all aerial
warfare mostly missile warfare, drone
warfare
uh mostly.
So it was not really a major major
full-scale war but there is a high
likelihood of India and Pakistan going
to war in my opinion in the next 1 to 3
years. 1 2 3 years right
and uh war in Indoacific. Now when you
say Indo-Pacific you obviously mean
something wider than India Pakistan I
don't foresee India and China going to
war right now in the near future at
least but what about the Indopacific
region like you say by that we if we
take India and Pakistan out of the
equation and Indian India and China out
of the equation we're obviously
discussing the China Korea Taiwan Japan
situation
right is there a likelihood of war
I would say it would be stupid for China
to get embroiled in a war over there. It
would be stupid for China to make a move
on Taiwan at this point in time. Wait
another decade or two, then take Taiwan.
It is it is stupid to do it right now.
So I don't see a war happening
in in East Asia
unless something is done to provoke
China which China can't do anything
about which crosses certain Chinese red
lines for example Japan going nuclear
for example and I don't know so you see
you see Japan is completely in the in
American control they are the Americans
can make Japan do whatever they want and
they can also make Korea do whatever
they want but Korea is not a military
power Japan is so it all depends on the
US. Do they want to provoke China
into some kind of war in the
Asia-Pacific region, right? Using
proxies such as Japan and South Korea,
maybe Taiwan, if the Americans succeed
in doing that, that could hurt
Russia, sorry, China to a certain
extent. U
but China will be obviously cautious
about this. So I think the there's a
high likelihood of war between India and
Pakistan in the next uh couple of years
or 3 years. Apart from that I don't
really see a major war erupting anywhere
else unless the Americans do something
magical and induce China to go to war
with Japan or somebody.
Aries Manticor says, "Could Russia
trigger a cold NATO conflict with Poland
and Sweden if the Ukraine conflict ends,
a similar frozen conflict, but with
small NATO countries? Would the US
follow up with the treaty in this
scenario?
I would say it's not in Russia's
interest
to be in a perpetual state of war.
Right?
So when it comes to nations like Poland
and Sweden, these nations are part of
NATO and NATO has whatever clause the
treaty right that an attack on one
member of NATO is an attack on all
members of NATO and if one nation is
attacked that's a member of NATO all
other nations that are members of NATO
need to come to its rescue and fight the
aggressor. So if Russia initiates a
conflict with Poland for example, well
that would be stupid because now you
fighting directly with NATO and that
won't end the way the Ukraine conflict
is going to end
and it makes no sense for Russia to do
that. Makes no sense. Uh because now
you're going to have the full might of
NATO directly against you. The Ukraine
conflict is a proxy conflict. It is
Ukrainians dying for NATO. But now
Poland and see the the west is is is the
past few years they've been transforming
Poland into a major military power.
Poland now is the most powerful has the
most powerful military in Europe in
Western Europe even more powerful than
Germany. There's a reason why this has
been done. Let's take a look at the map.
Okay,
if you see the map, what do you have
west of Ukraine and Belarus? you have
Poland. So Poland is the next frontier.
So the west is worried that if Russia
for whatever reason takes over Ukraine
and Belelleros is already kind of you
know an ally of Russia then they could
make a try to make a move on Eastern
Europe and all these nations used to be
part of the Warso pact Poland, Czech
Republic, Slovakia
um Hungary and so on.
So that's why they are they are
transforming Poland into a major
military power and it would be I would
say not very wise of Russia to start a
conflict with Poland. I mean what do you
get? What does Russia get from a
conflict with Poland? What's the point
of an ending war?
A war, a military conflict makes sense
if it has clear political and military
objectives
that are in line with your national
interest.
Now, is a war with Poland, Sweden,
whatever, is it in line with Russia's
national interest? What are the military
objectives? What are the political
objectives? I'm not quite sure. So, it
doesn't make sense.
Struggler says, "What do you think about
Trump and Bill Clinton,
Donnie and Bubba?" I don't think about
those two in that sense. I Yeah.
[laughter]
What can I say? And this is not the
forum to discuss that. I discussed these
things on Twitter. [laughter]
Looks like it's Looks like the rumors
are true. Good God. I don't know what
sort of nation the United States is
really. I don't get their culture.
Yikes.
James, my duke, my good friend James is
back. China called our land Tanju,
meaning heavenly. James, uh, what land
are you from? Are you Indian? The
Chinese called India heavenly. Tanju
means the center of heaven or heavenly
abode or whatever. Right.
Yeah. The Chinese when referring to
India called it Tanju during the Tang
dynasty era. heavenly. That is indeed
true. Yeah, but that's India, not the
UK, not not England, India. [laughter]
Uh Nick Dreams says the US is betting
big on AI. What will be the geopolitical
implications if it turns out to be a bad
bet or a bet that takes a decade to pay
off? We've had similar things, decade,
big data, climate change, etc. Climate
change was a passing fad. It's indeed a
thing. Climate change is indeed a
reality. No question about that. But
there was a tremendous amount of focus
on climate change and now it's not
there.
Big data.
There was a lot of hype about big data.
Was that hype justified? Of course it
was justified. Now big data is no longer
a buzzword that is in vogue. But big
data is the foundation of artificial
intelligence. Without big data there is
no AI.
Yes, the US is betting big on AI. Why is
China betting so big on AI?
Can AI be a bad bet? Absolutely not. AI
is a transformative technology.
A thousand years from today, historians
will write about the preAI era and the
post AI era.
And we see for us, what do we see? What
do we what kind of AI are we aware of?
Chad GPT and what recently Gemini
something has come out and uh there is
and clothe and there is the Chinese uh
whatever the names are right we know ch
is the most famous so we most people are
aware of you know that you can chat with
chat GPT ask questions and it tells you
of stuff and yeah nice that's not the
only thing AI is there are different AIs
that you are not aware of there There
are military AIs. What will a military
AI do? Is going to decide for you what
is the best strategy in a complicated
geopolitical situation, let's say, or in
a complicated war situation. What is the
best strategy to use in real time that
will outsmart your enemy.
It it can do game theory in real time.
You see, game theory is nice when you're
doing the prisoners dilemma and whatnot.
You can calculate those situ situations
easily, reasonably easily. You can do a
Nash Nash equilibrium and what not. But
when it comes to complex situations with
so many different factors, you need a
very high intelligence to do the game
theoretical calculations
and you know give you the dominant
strategies.
So AI can do that. So AI is not going to
be a bad bat, a bad bet. There's an AI
arms race going on and whichever nation
comes out on top is going to rule the
world for the next 1,000 years
potentially.
How do we decide who has won? The nation
that achieves AGI and ASI first is the
is the winner. Once you reach there, you
will simply outpace everybody else and
you will prevent the others from
catching up with you. So AI is not going
to be a bad bad bet
and it's it's not going to take a decade
to pay off. It's paying off right now,
but you're not aware of it. That's the
point. You're not supposed to know these
things. These things happen behind
closed doors. There are AI systems you
can't imagine that are currently in
existence.
Okay. General Dwayne says, "How in South
Korea the people are detached from
culture?" Look, I have answered this
question multiple times and it's not a
geopolitical question. Sir, please let's
discuss geopolitics today. All right, I
I took this question just a couple of
live streams ago in detail. So, you can
check out maybe episode 30
either 306 or 304.
Bu says, do you think the Japanese or
German public deep inside know that
their country is a vasal state? Some of
them are aware of it. Some of them who
are still able to think critically will
be aware of it. Right? Uh but most
people in any nation they just go with
the flow. See what what do people want
in life? First of all ask yourself this
what do people want in life? Firstly
people are the same everywhere.
And now you will say what do I mean by
that? Human beings are the same no
matter which country you go to. Whether
you go to African nations, Asian
nations, subcontinent of India, Europe,
East Europe, Western Europe, North
Africa, North America, South America,
wherever you go in the world, people are
the same. Now, what do I mean by that?
Everybody wants the same things. They
want a nice comfortable life. They want
a decent income. They want decent living
standards. They want a good future for
their children. That's what everybody
wants in every country.
Okay. Now if you look at the state of
the conditions in Germany and Japan,
these are both first world nations.
These are the two nations that were the
major
you could say losers of the second world
war.
Right? Both were devastated. Then the
Americans helped these two nations rise
back on their feet. Gave them first
world status and standards. Allowed them
to reach those those standards. allowed
those economies to become robust again,
right? But kept the nations enslaved
because they are worried about these
nations. So the situation is that the
ordinary people have good living
standards way better than in India. They
have comfort. They have things that you
would call luxuries in India. They have
high incomes.
They have a well German, forget about
Germany now, but they had a you know
peaceful
law and order and whatnot. Maybe not the
case in Germany anymore because the
immigration thing, but whatever
the rule of law, all of those things.
So, as long as you have all those
things, you will not complain too much,
right? And you have elections that
happen on a regular basis.
And then you have the education system
that tells you that you know your
country was evil and the Americans are
the beneficial benevolent benevolent
oppress benevolent friends of ours. So
you are in this nice cozy cocoon.
So most people will be happy believing
all that. And you know when somebody
points out some you know facts that go
contrary to what you believe it makes
you very uncomfortable. You you want to
not think too much. You can just label
put labels on those people. You are
conspiracy theorists blah blah blah all
that stuff. So most people don't know
about this. Most people don't care about
this. But there'll be some people who
are aware. I mean recently uh somebody
pointed out last week to me that there
was some Japanese politician in
parliament who said that Japan is a
colony of the US, a vasal of the US. Uh
so I did happen to eventually see that
uh video clip and yeah that person was
an MP in Japan who was pointing out that
Japan is a colony of the US and then the
Japanese prime minister stands up and
she says that no Japan is a sovereign
nation. Well we all know that's a
convenient fiction isn't it?
WBR says do you know about the Clinton
Leinsky scandal? You see, like I said, I
am not a news surfer.
[laughter]
That happened 20, 30 years ago. How many
years? Of course, they know about it.
What's the point? How what does it have
to do with geopolitics?
Come on, man. This is this was all over
the I mean, everyone knows about that.
Bhaskar Bandit says Poland's
demographics have not been re-engineered
so much yet, unlike other parts of the
EU. Is it because they agreed to pump
their military-industrial complex
against the fake Russia is coming
threat? Potentially. So there are two
nations in
you could say western you could say US
controlled Europe that have refused to
allow these immigrants into their into
their nation. One is Poland, the other
is Hungary. And both nations have to pay
fines to to to the dictatorship in
Brussels because they don't want the
immigrants. I think the fines are like
several million dollars per day or
something, but they are willing to pay
it. Um,
so why is this being tolerated? First of
all, if you pay the fine, what can they
do about it, right? It's the price of
freedom, I suppose. and u
and maybe there's some there's some kind
of tacit understanding that you know we
don't change our demographics and we
allow you to
to bulk up our military-industrial
complex and to turn Poland into a
fortress against Russia. Maybe there
could be that sort of understanding but
obviously none of that is known in the
public domain naturally.
Ankita G says, "Your opinion on the US
boycotting the G20 summit or alleged
persecution of whites in the in South
Africa. Secondly, South Africa
proceeding with declaration without US
nod. What do you think a really bold
step?" Wow. Okay. So, like I said, I
have not really
um
I've not really um
studied what's happening in the G20
summit right now. I'll I'll do that in
my own sweet time in a week or so, but
Okay. So the US has boycotted the G27. I
remember Trump a few months ago was
putting out this videos
on X and his social media. What is truth
social or something? Videos about why
it's being persecuted
in South Africa. There's a white
genocide happening allegedly in South
Africa. That's what he was claiming. And
Elon Musk was was in agreement with
Donald Trump.
So is that why the US has boycotted the
G20 summit? is has the US boycotted it
has I know that Trump hasn't gone but
has is there no US presence at all so I
am not aware of this the G20 summit is
something that's happening right now or
it has it may just have ended I'll I I
don't surf the news I don't try to keep
track of the latest information in real
time I take my time to see what's
happening so I'm not sure what the deal
is but in case the US has boycotted the
G20 summit like clearly it has okay
makes no difference
the US is will the US will continue to
rule the the way it does and whether it
participates in the G20 summit or not
makes no real difference in the outcomes
in in the world. Right? Trump is happy
playing his game of tariffs. He is
trying to achieve a certain uh outcome
in the Ukraine conflict, a ceasefire or
[laughter]
as per his proposal. He's trying to
counterbalance China. He's trying to
encircle India and so on. All that is
going on and G20 summit makes no
difference actually for him. So it's
okay. It's not important for him. Maybe
the G7 is more important for the US than
the G20.
So yeah, if if that's the case, then it
makes no difference to the US whether
they participate or not. And South
Africa proceeding with a declaration
without US N. What do you think the
really bold step?
Um look, a declaration is a bunch of
words, right? Who cares about
declarations? I have always emphasized
the difference between words and
actions.
You may put out declarations or
whatever. At the end of the day, they
are symbolic. It's words. Do you know
how these things are drafted? A bunch of
diplomats and bureaucrats come together
from various countries and then they
have intense negotiations all night
negotiations about what words to use in
which order to use them.
That goes on for multiple days and at
the end of the day there's a great
consensus. Yes, we have done it. We have
found the right order of words.
I have seen these G20 declarations.
It's a bunch of words, right? It has no
real massive
outcome on
on the shape of the world, on the shape
of history, it's okay. No big deal. So
if the if the South Africans have
proceeded with a declaration without the
US not then it's not a really bold step.
The US also doesn't really care. They
won't really punish South Africa for it.
They will punish South Africa if South
Africa does some takes some actions that
are counter to American interests
actions. Let's say that South Africans
allow Russian mining companies in South
Africa. Now that's something that
crosses red lines. Let's say South
Africa allows certain Chinese activities
in South Africa that cross perceived US
red lines. That sort of stuff will will
invite retaliation. A declaration a
bunch of words. No one cares.
Kiran Murray says ISRO scientists are bu
are building atomisus AI. Huh? Let's
let's find out. I thought in ISRO you
had engineers, right? ISRO is an
engineering organization.
Rocket engineers. Let's see what this
is. Isro
atmesus
AI. What is this?
Atomsus AI. India's young innovators to
launch atomsus AI next gen India origin
intelligence platform built with ISRO
something ISRO level engineering
India blah blah blah blah blah atom
enough
Indian origin re so these engineers have
research exposure under ISRO it's not
under ISRO the the development of this
atomsus AI is not under ISO ISRO it's
engineers who have exposure under ISRO.
Okay, that's different.
Affordable, powerful, sovereign, yeah,
alternative, etc. Empower students,
creators, families, professionals, one
unified ecosystem.
Okay, we'll see about that. Too early to
pass any judgment. I'll have to see what
this AI is. What is it capable of? You
see,
AIs come in different flavors. some
flavors are not for public consumption.
If this is another chatbot kind of model
etc. I mean it's a good it's a good
initiative it's a good step but you have
to take it forward. So I'm I'm glad that
people are taking the initiative but
it's not ISRO scientists who are doing
it first of all. It is some a bunch of
people who have had exposure to ISRO in
the past who are building it. That's
great. That's great.
But you can't build
an AI that is a competitor
to chat GPD or or or claude or
Gemini or the Chinese systems with small
money. You need really large num amounts
of money to do that. So that's what
India needs. India needs to invest
billions of dollars worth of money into
AI.
um a number of a bunch of entrepreneurs
doing it is a great step but I hope that
if they do a good job of it they should
get more funding to create a proper
competitor to the American and Chinese
systems okay says can you explain about
the Gaddafi case in the ICC
don't remember what it was that was in
the 80s was it the locker bombing I
suppose that was it there was this uh
was it the panam aircraft
that was uh blown up over Lockerby in
Ireland. Was it Panama? It was blue
because I've seen the wreckage when I
was a kid in the media. Obviously, I
didn't go there. Um [snorts] let's see.
Docker Bombing.
Was it PANAM? Panama 103, right? Yeah,
my memory serves me right. It was a blue
thing. Pan American Airlines. no longer
exists. And did this eventually lead to
a case against Gaddafi in the
International
Criminal Court possibly and then
and then some Libyan citizens were
sanctioned or jailed or whatever. I
don't remember the details but yeah
something like that. It's been a long
time, hasn't it? Uh Phantom says, "I see
a lot of players in the Indian Ocean.
What can happen if Indian influence on
the Indian Ocean slips off? It'll be bad
for India.
You see, if you have
an erosion of Indian influence in the
Indian Ocean, then you'll have other
players who become dominant dominant
actors in the Indian Ocean region. Let's
take a look at the map quickly.
[clears throat]
What is the Indian Ocean region first of
all?
So the Indian Ocean region is
the Indian subcontinent. It is
the west coast of the sea of Sawashtra
or the so-called Arabian Sea. And then
you have the East Africa coast. You have
Madagascar. You have Mauritius and Runo.
Then you have uh Perth in Australia
where cricket matches last only two days
apparently. And then you have Indonesia
right Sumatra and then you have the
Andaman Sea and the great Kolinga Mahas
Saga that's the Indian Ocean region but
the area of our interest is you know the
western and eastern Indian Ocean which
is the so-called Arabian Sea and the the
so-called Bay of Bengal. So if India's
influence er you know there's an erosion
of that over here then you will have
other players becoming major actors over
here. Let's say the Chinese Navy becomes
a major player here. They can make life
difficult for India. We have see we have
all kinds of shipments coming in
maritime shipments coming in to various
ports in India. We have a port in
Gujarat. Mundra is it? It is a major
port in Gujarat. Mundra we also have uh
port in Mumbai, Navasha. We have other
ports. We have a major port, trans
shipment port coming up in the undermans
and all of that. If the Chinese become a
dominant maritime player here, they can
took off our
our shipments and that becomes a problem
for us. Let's say that the Pakistanis
suddenly in the next 5 years have more
and better submarines than India and
once again it's a major problem for
India and they can create havoc with our
shipping lanes and whatnot.
So you can see it's it's a it's a
disaster for India. India has to control
this region which is why we need more
ships. We need better ships. We need a
diversity of ships. We need distributed
lethality of you know not just one kind
of ship. You don't want concentrated le
lethality. You want your lethality to be
distributed over a wide area of the
ocean. What is lethality?
To make a long story short, lethality
means missiles, naval missiles. Yeah.
Naval firepower.
So yeah, we need to ensure that our
influence does not decline in the Indian
Ocean region. We need to augment our
influence and our control of the region.
Minimalist Maverick says what's going to
happen to Antarctica? What's in the mind
of Russia, China, US, India annexing
regarding this? I want it to be Indian
territory and I want my own house there.
Well, you know what? I would love to
have a house, one of my holiday homes in
Antarctica. I can go there for half an
hour every year. [laughter]
It's frighteningly cold. What's going to
happen to Antarctica?
See, everybody wants a piece of
Antarctica.
And various nations have claims
on Antarctica. Would you like to see the
claims? Let's let's take a look at that.
Okay.
Argentina has a claim. Chile has a
claim. Let's take a look at claims.
Territorial claims on Antarctica. Let's
see.
The the English have a claim. Would you
believe it?
I suppose even the French would have
claims. Argentina, Australia, Australia
has a claim. Yes, Chile, France, New
Zealand has a claim on Antarctica.
Norway, who the hell are the Norwegians
to claim Antarctic territory?
So here we have various claims which
most of them are jokes. I mean the UK
claiming Antarctica is a joke, isn't it?
Absolute laughable reasonable joke. UK,
Norway, who does who do the Norwegians
think they are claiming Antarctica?
Australia, I can understand that.
France, well, they have territories, you
know, in the southern Indian Ocean. Uh,
New Zealand, well, we could understand
they can at least make a nominal claim.
Argentina,
UK, once again, Chile also, right? Uh,
so that is the deal. Now, you see, most
of these nations are in no condition.
They're in no position
to actually act on these claims. These
are all nominal claims just for names
sake. to to play the game of, you know,
to pretend to be a big power. The UK
claiming Antarctic territory. What kind
of a joke is that? In Norway, [laughter]
New Zealand, I mean, no disrespect to
these nations, but it it is not it's not
going to work out for them, right? If
they try to actually
act on those claims. So, what's going to
happen to Antarctica?
See, there are certain nations, several
nations that have bases in Antarctica.
These bases are typically u
observatories, research sta stations,
scientific research stations. The
Americans have plenty of this. The
Chinese have it. Uh India also has at
least a couple of uh Antarctic stations
that are typically manned around the
year if I'm not mistaken. Hopefully
around the year. I would be disappointed
if it's only 6 months a year or
whatever. We'll see. The Chinese have
that. Russians, the Russians have it. So
the nations that actually maintain bases
on Antarctica, those have to be taken
more seriously. Let's take a look at
which nations have antactic bases.
Right? Let's see. List
list of nation. Come on. Spelling of
nations with Antarct
Antarctic
bases. Let's see how many we have. New
Zealand. Okay. Australia. Chile.
France. Norway. Argentina. Chile again.
Germany. Nice. Japan. Nihon, good, good
to have you. Um, Ross, okay, let's see.
That's nonsense. Research stations in
Antarctica, how many do we have a list?
Do we have a list? Okay, US 25%.
Argentina, Chile, UK, France, Australia,
Russia, Japan, China, Italy, South
Africa, India has only 1.89%.
So, India is has a presence there. As
always, India is all about slogans and
symbolism. We have a couple of stations.
Yes. But we don't take it seriously.
That's how India does everything thus
far. I would like to that that to
change. So that's the situation. If
there is I think there's a treaty that
says that Antarctica has to remain um
neutral territory and no nation can
actually uh seek to occupy it. And these
treaties well they will continue to
exist as long as the current world order
exists. If there is a major upheaval in
the world order, well, some nations may
make a move on Antarctica. Those who
those that can so what's going to
happen? We'll see about that. Thus far,
it is neutral territory.
Abinav Kulkarnney says Abijjit Abnit
detailed geopolitics podcast. Well,
okay. Thank you for the suggestion. I am
not really doing podcast that much
anymore.
Very rarely, very infrequently.
So, we'll see. But anyway, thank you for
the suggestion, sir. Duva Batnager.
Well, thank you very much. Thank you.
WBR says, "Is MN
is Mongolia a safeguard for Russia
against China? Groups like the Buryats,
Yakut, Tuans, etc. are getting
militarized due to war." Which war is a
war. Where is it?
Ukraine war. So, is it a problem for
China if it decided to go in? You see,
yeah, there good question. We'll go to
the map.
[clears throat]
Ask yourself a question.
Okay, very pragmatic geopolitical
question. Why does Mongolia still exist?
You see, there's a story, right? When
Stalin was shown a map of India, when
Joseph Stalin was shown a map of the
Indian subcontinent, he asked, "What is
this little island to the south of
India?" And the Indian ambassador said,
"Sar, you see this is Sri Lanka. It is a
separate nation." And Stalin said, "Why
is it a separate nation?
If you are a great power, why don't you
take it? Why is it a separate nation?
Why is it independent? The Indian
ambassador had no no answer to that. So
why is Mongolia which is sandwiched
between massive Russia and massive
China, why is it independent?
It is independent
because it's a buffer state. It was once
the greatest empire in human history.
Today it is unfortunately and sadly
a nation that's almost powerless.
doesn't have a great military
and you see it's not geopolitically
relevant except as a buffer state
between Russia and China. About half of
Mongolia is occupied by China. The
Chinese call it southern Mongolia and
it's under Chinese occupation and there
is a part of Mongolia that's north of
present day Mongolia that has been
incorporated into Russian territory. So
historically Mongolia was much larger.
Now it's been takes have been taken out
of it and whatever is left is a buffer
state. It's still massive.
So, so why does it exist in the shape
and format that it does? Because the
Chinese and the Russians need something
between them. If they have a much longer
border, there is a much higher
likelihood of Russia and China going to
war. So, it's better to have a buffer
state between them. A nation that can't
threaten anybody and you allow it to
exist. And I can go into the history of
Mongolia and what happened during the
Soviet era, etc., But that's maybe for a
different day.
Yuvraj Gupta says Jan 25 you said
raising standards session.
Did I
should we have a live stream about how
to raise your standards? I suppose we
could do that. Yeah, I did kind of say
something like that. So what I did was I
did all those live streams, right? I did
work with me, study with me live
streams. that was raising your
standards. What was the purpose of those
50 live streams I did? I'll I'll show
you once again.
So the past 2 3 months I've stopped that
now but the past 2 three months I did
those live streams which are no longer
visible. Uh one second I had opened this
for a second latest let's see are those
live streams visible anymore? I think I
have unlisted those but you will find
those live streams. or here
if I open up the playlists. One second.
So I'm not sure it will be somewhere
there. The point is why did I have those
those live streams
that was how to raise your standards?
See if you want to achieve something big
you have to spend a lot of time working
on it right and that was the purpose of
those live streams. So that that was
kind of what I did you know eight hour
eight hours eight hour sessions of me
writing.
So the objective was to demonstrate that
to achieve something to to create
something you have to spend a lot of
time and effort doing that. So that was
kind of along the lines of raising your
standards. But I could perhaps do a live
stream specifically dedicated to how to
raise your standards. We'll we'll see
about that. The Kish is a new member.
Well, welcome sir. Let's let us welcome
the Kish to the the channel's
membership. Thank you very much for
becoming a member. I really appreciate
that.
Okay. Biju says, Biju Sika says, "What
do you think about the BRRI project? How
is it going and when will it be
successful and will it be successful?"
The BARRI project has been on for a very
long time, hasn't it? The belt and road
u the belt and road initiative of China.
What was the objective of the Barri
project? The objective of the BR project
was to create a massive amount of
infrastructure in Eurasia that would
connect China
um with
the rest of the Euro Eurasian nations
and it would allow China to export its
goods to all the Eurasian nations and uh
that the sort of thing. So if you
control the infrastructure of industry,
if you control the infrastructure of uh
commerce
then you control much of the economy of
the region right and you have and you
get ready access to all kinds of
resources maybe raw materials and all
that. So that was that is the purpose of
the BRI project. It's to increase
Chinese influence and power across
Eurasia. They have a complimentary
project called the maritime silk road
which seeks to create maritime trade
routes and shipping lanes between China
and various nations including African
nations to extract
uh natural resources from those nations
and obviously all the objective of all
of this is to increase China's power.
Now what do I think about it? It's a
great initiative.
It it shows that China is an ambitious
nation. It's a nation with a specific
very very clear vision for the future
and it shows China has great leadership.
But how has this gone thus far? It's not
worked out very well for China. Many
nations have stopped participating in
the Barri and if you look at the the the
Pakistan portion of the BRI, the China
Pakistan economic corridor, it's it's
not really worked out at all, right?
It's not paid off the way the Chinese
wanted it to pay off and so and so on.
So it's it's not gone very well for
China. That's the problem that the
Chinese have faced thus far.
Uh Kish Krishi exe says how can soft
power of a nation affect geopolitics.
Um so [clears throat] this is not a
criticism of you Krishi exe but
what I have consistently observed is
that Indians are obsessed with soft
power. Soft power. Soft power. Okay. I'm
not trying to criticize you. I'm just
putting forth an observation of not you
specifically. It's a pattern that you
see across all Indians or or most
Indians that we are obsessed with soft
power. I'll tell you what is the
relevance of soft power in geopolitics.
Minimal.
Soft power is
useless without hard power. If you don't
have hard power but you have soft power
it gives you nothing whatsoever in
geopolitics but you if you have hard
power then soft power can sometimes
augment it sometimes you can get things
done through soft power if you have hard
power so if I have a big stick but I
talk to you nicely sir let's sit
together let's work it out I need these
things from you would you be so kind as
to give it to me then maybe you will
give it to me. So I'm not using hard
power here to convince you or to bully
you. I'm talking to you nicely and I'm
convincing you through my good behavior.
That is soft power. But if I did not
have that stick behind my back or at my
disposal, then you would not listen to
me. Right? So that's how it works. Soft
power is useless and pointless without
hard power to back it up.
Uh right angle says please tell other
delusions of people of Bhat live.
Well we can discuss that in a different
live stream. Today we're going to
discuss geopolitics not delusions of
people of bat which are there are plenty
of of course. Uh so yeah even yesterday
somebody had asked me reminded me about
that. So maybe I can perhaps do another
video about that. Yeah. So maybe I will
clip I will take a screenshot of of this
comment and maybe in a future live
stream I can discuss a few more
delusions of the people of Parat. Sure.
Om Susan Baratwaj says a life is
measured in what we give
not take. Let time flow through you to
others. Well okay that's not a question
but it's a statement and I agree with
you.
Well it's up to you. You know you can
measure your life in whichever way you
want but I think this is a good way of
measuring life
what what is the purpose of life is what
many people ask right what's the purpose
of life so you can decide what what the
purpose of your life is for but for me I
would say my life has been a good life
if I am able to contribute more to
society than I take from society I think
that would be a life well-lived so yeah
I that kind of echoes what you're saying
here so yes I agree with
Karan well Karan has no question but
thank you so much Karan really
appreciate it. Thank you sir. Anime Paul
says today is my birthday. Well first of
all Animesh happy birthday to you and
wish you many many happy returns of this
fantastic day for you. Uh I'm a tech
worker doing well in life. I'm deeply
grateful for what I what I have knowing
not everyone has this privilege. How can
I become a better person with higher
standards? Okay. Okay. So this is not
geopolitics but since it's your since
it's your birthday I'll answer in brief.
How can you become a better person with
higher standards? Don't compromise.
Don't lie to yourself. All of us in some
way or the other. We kind of lie to
ourselves, right? We make some promises
to ourselves and then then we break
those promises. And what is a
compromise? It's breaking the promises
you make to yourself. You know what
you're capable of what? What you're
capable of. You know what you want to
achieve in life. Maybe you have some
dreams, some hopes, some aspirations
and if you compromise on those things by
settling for an easier life or maybe
settling because of whatever reasons
then you are compromising and that
you're lowering your standards. So you
have to be uncompromising.
It's very very hard. It's easy. It's
very easy to say these things. It's very
hard to do that in real life. But only
the hard things make you better, right?
So you and sometimes you have to
compromise certain there are certain
times when you don't have the resources
at your disposal to achieve what you
want to achieve. So maybe you delay what
you want to achieve but you don't
postpone it forever. Right? So that's
the kind of thing it is. I mean I can go
on about this in detail but the main
thing is don't lie to yourself. Whatever
promises you make to yourself, you you
keep those promises to yourself
otherwise you will lose your own
selfrespect
and don't compromise with uh whatever
your core goals and objectives are.
Don't please don't become people
pleaser. That is also one sign of
lowering standards. Okay, so these are
some some of the things. All the best
Animesh and once again happy birthday to
you. Bhuven says why no government
action on anti-Indian
online racism?
Well, the government of India can only
act within the geographical confines of
India. India's sovereignty is within its
geographical confines. Right? Now, when
there is
some activity coming from outside of
India, what can India do about it? Can
the government of India take action
against people legally? Can the
government of India legally take action
against somebody who is in a different
country? What can we do? We could
perhaps request the government of that
country to do something. But if it's a
democratic country then the government
of that country will say that these are
people who are exercising their rights
as per the law of our country and in our
country we have freedom of speech. So
they will say what whatever they want to
say. We can't we can't do anything about
it. We are friends of yours but we can't
control all our people. Then what do you
do about it?
The real reason this is a problem for us
is is because we don't control the
platforms on which there is anti-India
online racism. All these social media
platforms, we don't control them. We
don't own them. We didn't build them
because we have been sitting doing
something else.
We have never bothered to build our own
platforms that are as good or even
better than what the West has built. We
don't have that ambition, right?
That's the problem. So, what can the
government do about it? How will the
government see you can't ask the
government to build a Twitter or a
Facebook?
Private entrepreneurs have to do that.
And there are people with these ideas,
but they who will fund them. It's high
risk, right? India, we don't want risk.
We don't want risk. We don't like risk
over there. There is a very low appetite
for risk in India. Very low risk
tolerance threshold. we have we want
guaranteed returns. So that's why you
you see if you go to Silicon Valley
there's a very high appetite for risk.
Um
angel investors they typically spread
their bets on let's say 20 companies and
even if two of those bets turn out to be
good they're going to make their money
back. But that mindset doesn't exist in
India. We have venture capital in India
and all but their mindset is different.
So that's where we are. Any solutions as
current to pollution problem pan India?
Well, that's a long big topic. I can't
answer that in detail. Um
what's the solution? One solution is we
go full on full in all in on nuclear
power. See right now a lot of the
electricity we generate is through uh
coal
based power plants. We we have to burn
coal for that right
and if you could move to nuclear
then that that could uh you know reduce
some of the pollution and there are so
many other things we can move to
electric vehicles then because see if
you move to electric vehicles completely
but your electricity electricity still
comes from fossil fuels then it's not
going to end the pollution so there is
that there are many other factors which
we can take which we can think of
NK says who is more powerful prime
minister or supreme court of India. This
is not a geopolitical question, sir.
This is a question about the internal
matters of India which I don't discuss.
See, I can't fight every battle. I can't
talk about everything. I speak about
three very broad topics. Geopolitics,
history and science. I will not discuss
Indian politics. I will not discuss
these internal matters of India. That is
not my my battlefield. So, no comments.
No comments. Sorry.
Uh DRC, thank you sir or ma'am. Uh the
question is is Anglo
uh is the Anglo-Saxon Empire trying to
alter Indian history, anthropology and
epistemology using state sanctioned
racism? What about never do an enemy a
small injury by Makyave?
Um
is the Anglo-Saxon Empire trying to
alter? See what they're trying to do?
What they're not trying to do? They have
been doing it for the past couple of
centuries. They have set the narrative
about India, about India's past, about
India's society, about India's culture.
They have fooled you all and the world
that there is a very evil cast system in
India.
Four four casts.
They instituted those casts,
right?
They made it part of the Indian legal
system, the Indian government governance
system and after 1947 we so the point is
they have written our history for us and
we teach that
to our students. They have set the
narrative about everything that is to do
with India, about India's history, about
India's culture, like I said,
everything. And now we also have racism
that's coming out from various places.
Now, one interesting thing that's
happened in the past couple of days on X
or Twitter is that every account now
shows the country of origin.
So, you'll see a lot of these anti-India
accounts, if you look at the country of
origin, it'll show South Asia. So you
can choose to show your country or your
geographical region and obviously
Twitter is an American company. So they
will show the they will say South Asia
not Indian subcontinent. So when an
account you find it to be South Asia
based and it is spewing hate against
Indians. It is guaranteed to be either
Pakistanis or Bangladesh.
Could be some other countries but mainly
Pakistanis and Bangladeshes.
So there are a lot of accounts like
these and those obviously are in line
with um you could say the Anglo-Saxon
agenda right
and and you have all these bots bot
farms and bot that that have been
amplifying that have been creating and
amplifying narratives against India the
past since the year 2022 mostly even
before that it was there but now it's
coordinated
um so they are not trying to alter
Indian history they have set the
narrative of Indian history. They have
set the set the standards of Indian
history. They have decided which dates
what happened. They have decided which
what was the date of the birth of the
Buddha, which day which year Kaneska
ruled, which years Kesan ruled
the Moran Empire. We don't even know if
those dates are correct.
There were multiple Chandra Guptas in
Indian history.
When Mastanis writes that I was at the
court of Chandra Kottos in Palibotra,
he's talking about a king called Chundra
Gupta in Palipatra.
But which Chundra Gupta? There have been
multiple Chandra Guptas in our history.
So what if the Morian Chandra Gupta
Moria was way before
before Alexander?
Yeah, that would place the date of
Chanaka also several centuries before it
would change the date of the birth of
Gotham Buddha. So all of this has been
decided by the west and we simply
slavishly blindly follow that. A lot of
this needs to be looked into
and yeah so by controlling what the what
you think of your history they control
your minds and that way that how that's
how they can control the entire country
the entire culture very powerful. Rohan
Sona says how Scandinavia became so rich
historically poor.
How did Scandinavia become so rich
historically it was poor?
Interesting question.
How did Scandinavia become so rich? I am
I'm not sure I can answer the question
right now and think of the historical
context in great detail. I will have to
re revisit this question. Interesting
question. But I haven't really studied
the historical um the flow of history.
Scandinavia
very interesting region but interesting
only in recent times. Historically like
you Yeah, you're right. It was not
really very prosperous. Yeah, I'm not
sure I can answer this question right
now, but interesting question. Maybe in
the future I can take it up. Krishna
Krish says, "Who really won the Cold
War?"
The United States won the Cold War. The
United States. James says, "European
people built all positive aspects of the
modern world due to their intelligence,
culture, and bravery. Our knowledge is
far more superior. I'm tired of I'm
tired of pretending. You have lived
there, right?" Yes, my dear friend
James, I have indeed lived in the west
on several occasions.
Uh, European people, fantastic people,
no question. Fantastic intelligence,
culture, bravery, uh, knowledge, very
superior. I'll tell you what, what the
Europeans did was they
excelled, they outperformed the rest of
the world in the systematic application
of organized violence.
Okay, that's what the westerners did.
And who excelled among the westerners?
It was the
who excelled at the organized and
systematic application of
large scale organized violence.
They they excelled at they mastered
this. the the the English are a race of
merchants who have guns and their
objective is to extract the maximum
profits out of any endeavor. That's what
the English are. And in the past 500
years that they destroyed the world,
plundered the world and amassed all the
wealth they could and kept the world and
impoverished the world, the rest of the
world and keep it kept it impoverished
and then constructed this this global
rules-based world order in which they
set the rules, the others followed the
rules and then they set the narratives
and then they wrote the history of the
world. That's how you claim that you are
that the west is superior. You see, let
let's look at this from a different
perspective. A perspective that's
different from any from anything I've
said before. Okay, hear me. Let me put
out a completely different perspective
from anything I have said before.
This is the age of Kali. This is the
Kali Yuga.
If you win in Kali Yuga, it doesn't mean
you're better. It means you're evil.
Right?
So victory in Kali Yuga means you are on
the side of the evil forces
and that's what's happened. But we're
going to retake the world sooner or
later. Anyway, James, I do appreciate
you very much. I do. Uh BU Saka says,
"Uh, are we going through the fourth
industrial revolution? How how long will
it last? How can we take advantage of
it?" Okay, industrial which industrial
revolution is this? Um
you had the industrial revolution in the
what 17th 18th centuries.
Um then you had I don't know which
industrial revolution this is. Um I'm a
little muddy on the history on the on
the the chronology of which was which.
Okay. But we are going through a massive
transformation. It's a transformative
period of um of human history because of
the technologies that have emerged.
Right. artificial intelligence. How long
will it last? How can we take advantage
of it?
This could last a thousand years. AI
could transform the world and whoever
wins the AI race, the race for AGI and
ASI could rule the world for a thousand
years if they don't get it wrong
catastrophically.
So
yeah, the next next couple of decades
are going to be transformative. We're
going to have the rise of very very
powerful AI systems and we also seeing
transformative leaps quantum leaps in
robotics technology. So you marry the
two artificial general intelligence or
or super intelligence with high
with cutting edge robotics you're going
to have a terminator like situation and
whoever is able to merge these two
technologies either the US or China
India is not a player so sadly right now
right now I hope it changes but India is
not a player right now so whoever wins
this race is going to rule the world for
a very long time
uh how long could it last like I said it
could last a thousand years at least a
century or two minimum
It's going to be the start of a new
imperial era. Who whoever wins this race
is going to start a new imperial era. A
new imperial cycle. An imperial cycle is
roughly two and a half centuries. That's
what history that's what history tells
us. So how can we take advantage of it?
By participating in the goddamn race.
India needs to participate. Is India a
player in robotics right now? No. No.
No. No. Is India a player in AI right
now? No. No sir. Not a toll sir. What
the hell are we doing? How can we take
advantage of it? By participating by
becoming a major player we are not a
Okay. Anyway,
UFX says Hungary minister says we will
pay no tax for illegals thoughts. Yeah,
that's been their policy for a very long
time for years.
I would say kudos for having a spine.
Yeah. Galler says, "Did you just 1984
eyes Germany and Poland?" I guess you're
right. Orion in spirit at least
spineless or not, but I hope that they
don't sell that commodity which fa did.
Did I 1984 is Germany and Poland? The
big brother Orwell, right? Orion in
spirit. Um
well Orwell
Orwell was kind of a visionary wasn't
he? He kind of saw the direction in
which the world could go and it's kind
of gone like that. If you look at the
European Union, you have a big brother
sitting in Brussels who controls what
happens, who decides what happens and
the people don't have the agency to
change that anymore. If you are a
citizen of of Italy, if you're a citizen
of Germany, if you're a citizen in in in
uh nonoccupied Ireland
and you don't want certain things in
your country, you are powerless to to do
anything about it. You don't have the
agency.
All you can do is obey, otherwise you're
going to face consequences. So, yeah,
that's that's what's happening. Germany,
Poland, not so much. Poland at least has
control over immigration. It's not
allowing any weird immigrants into into
into its across its borders, which is a
good thing.
So
yeah, that's the situation in Germany.
Yeah. What is that commodity that F uh
sold? I can't quite recall. Let's let's
let's
F.
Yeah,
FA of course. Uh F was um what is the
commodity that he sold? I can't remember
right now. It's been a while. Okay.
Selling your [laughter]
selling your soul to El Diabolo. Maybe
that. Okay. Da says, "Namaste. Will
debasement trade accelerate in 26?"
I I don't know. I'm really sorry. Can't
say. I not keeping track of any of this.
Sorry.
Um, Amisha says, "When will the black
hole and Maya chapter come next?" Long
time.
Yeah, it's been a while, hasn't it? See,
the mirror mirrors of Maya series, it's
it's not easy to write. You have to come
up with a new story, completely fresh
story each time. It's not something that
I can write one chapter a week. It's a
new story each time. It's a new short
story each time. I need a completely
different character and I have to think
about a really interesting story. So
that's difficult. It will not come.
Sometimes you may have a couple of
releases in a month, maybe sometimes
once in 3 months. I can't say for sure.
Black holes. [snorts]
I'm wondering what to do about the Black
Hole series right now. Obviously, I'll
cut I'm continuing it. I'm working on
that. But should I continue to release
each chapter as a standalone ebook or
should I now that I've released three? I
think three, right? Should I then now
just complete the book and release it at
one go? I I have to think about that. So
I'm still in the process of deciding
which way to release it. Should I
release it all at the end in the form of
a proper physical and ebook or should I
continue doing it one step at a time?
Let me decide and I'll get back to you
all. But thank you for reminding me
Amisha G
Sur is a new member. Well, thank you
very much Suresh G. I really appreciate
you becoming a member and I welcome you
to the channel. Thank you so much. I
appreciate your support sir. WBR
says, "Was Magnificent Nehu comparable
to Clinton or Trump?"
Well,
[laughter]
well, certain aspects were similarly
magnificent.
certain aspects of Shri Neuji's
personality of his multifaceted
personality were potentially reminiscent
of Shri uh Bill Clinton G or Shri Donald
Trump G certain aspects you see Mr.
Arrow was a very
very charismatic person. He was very
popular apparently with the ladies. So
these aspects seem to be [laughter]
uh kind of comparable.
Apart from that, I don't know.
[laughter]
Okay. Om Susant Badwaj says, "I pulled
that code of life and time from your
book. Honestly, it's a great read."
Okay. Okay. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So
that's why it echoed what I said. Well,
thank you very much for pointing that
out and I once again completely agree
with what you said. Thank you, G.
Uh, Lakshman Tahilyani says, "How much
time does India have to sort Pakistan
out?"
Um, how much time does India have to
sort Pakistan out? That's a good
question. 6 months, 1 year. The longer
we take to sort them out, the more of a
price we may have to pay. I would say 6
months to one year,
maximum 3 years. I would I would say 3
years is too late. That's why I said
earlier in this uh episode, right? I
foresee a war between India and Pakistan
in the next 1 to 3 years. I would say 6
months to one year we have to sort them
out otherwise it'll be too late.
Galler says Om Susant Bhardwaj I think
quoted Nila Nityan's DI. Okay. I'm not
sure. This is a conversation with
somebody else. All right. Okay. Um,
okay. It's It's to me. Is it? Okay. I'm
a little confused. What is is this a
question to me? I think quoted Nityan
said DIL. What's a DIL?
Yeah, I'm not sure what you're saying
here, but no questions like this. Okay,
no problem. Thank you. Um, satellite.
I'm not sure what that means, but okay.
satellite says, "Next, ask me anything
live stream. I have some questions.
Maybe I should do a generic ask me
anything live stream in which I take
questions about anything."
Sure, I I can do that. How about next
weekend I do an ask me a liveream which
will be a general live stream, not
specifically geopolitics. Sure. Okay,
done. This coming Sunday, let me make a
mental note of that. This coming Sunday
it will be a a freestyle live stream. No
specific topic. All right, I'll do that.
Thank you for the suggestion. UA Gupta
doesn't have a question. No problem sir.
Thank you very much for your
contribution. Thank you sir. The
scrummer says why don't we fence all our
borders? Well, the problem with fencing
all our borders is is that you can't
fence borders that are like 7 km high,
right? Or 5 km high across mountainous
terrain, glaciers, ice. Sometimes you
have borders in very hilly hilly regions
up and down, up and down forests and
waterfalls and whatnot. How do you how
do you fence that? Sometimes you can't.
If you go to the Himalayas, if you go
there physically and you see the
situation there, see the kind of
mountains we have, you'll understand
it's not possible to fence the borders
there. So there are practical reasons
why it's not possible always to fence
all the borders. As far as possible, we
should.
SK1 says, "Namaste. Namaste. And thank
you very much for your contribution.
Thank you so much.
James says there is more racism in India
than than there is in the EU. You see,
I'm not sure if it's more or less, but
there's no question about the fact that
there is racism in every nation.
It is there. It's it's a it's a fact of
life. There is some amount of racism in
every nation.
It it is what it is. It's human nature.
can't do anything about it. But I'm not
sure about India having more racism than
the EU. I'm not sure about that, James.
Not sure about that. Have you been to
the EU? You were The UK was a member of
the EU, wasn't it? Before Brexit
happened, Brexit.
The Europeans are pretty racist.
I know that for a fact. Depending on
which nation you're in, certain nations
are super racist. So I would say Indians
are way less racist actually than than
the average European. I would say the
average Indian is significantly less
racist than the average European. That
is something I can say from firsthand
experience.
Uh indig 3,000 kilog of rare earth
magnets enough for Israel. What is the
indig?
Um not sure what the question is. 3,000
kg of rare earth magnets is it enough
indigenous
is it enough for ISRO? I'm not sure. I'm
not sure if if you're asking if 3,000 kg
of indigenous rare earth magnets is it
enough for ISRO? I am not sure because
I'm not sure how ISRO is using rare
earths or neodyinium magnets or whatever
it is. For what purpose? I'm not sure. I
can't can't answer the question. Right.
Sharale says how did we evolve from
apes?
Well,
I'm not sure how it is connected to
geopolitics, but we evolved through
natural selection. We evolved through
the the need to survive.
And evolution doesn't happen over two
weeks, right? It happens over hundreds
of thousands of years.
So, it happened over time. the
environmental factors and the pressures
of natural selection and the survival of
the fittest. All these pressures and the
changing environment of of the earth and
the evolving uh threat p scenarios for
humans all of these things they shaped
our evolution and that's how it
happened.
Um Om Susan Bhadwat says it is all
related to the book borrowed time the
first book of the mirror mirrors of
Maya.
Got it. Got it. Got it. Thank you. Thank
you once again. All right, that brings
me to the end of the live stream.
I've taken I suppose all the questions.
Okay, there's one more question uh from
the super chat. Your opinion of EU of
the European Union is similar to Eva
Flardinger
Brooking
Brook. Who is Eva Flingerbrook?
I'm not sure who this uh person lady is,
but okay. I'll maybe I'll check out who
this person is and what u her I think
it's a her she what her opinions are.
I'll check it out. All right. Thank you
very much for letting me know. And that
brings me to the end of the uh super
chats. Yeah, we have almost reached two
and a half hours. So, I think it's a
it's a good time to end. But let me take
one final question by Aayush.
We are getting a subtle hint. Are we
getting subtle hints of a nuclear Japan?
I earlier made a video on this before.
What's my opinion? How will it change
the geopolitical equation in Southeast
in East Asia?
I think you could have a nuclear Japan
in the next two to two to three years.
It would be in line with what I said in
in the earlier video. It al it would
also be in line with uh what Henry
Kissinger had predicted in the year 2022
or 2023 that they will have a nuclear
armed Japan in the next 5 years.
So if that happens it will be a
significant setback for China
and I'm I'm sure the Chinese will throw
a big tantrum but what can they do about
it? So it will significantly change the
geopolitical balance of power in East
Asia. See Japan is a shadow nuclear
power. It has the technology. It has the
technological knowhow. If Japan wants,
if it is given the go-ahhead by the
United States, it can have indigenous
nuclear weapons next week
and highquality nuclear weapons. Japan
is one of the most technologically
advanced nations in the world. So they
can have it anytime they they're allowed
to. If this happens, then this will
significantly alter the balance of power
in East Asia. And I see that happening
in the next two to three years, perhaps
even sooner. Yeah.
And there's one more super chat. So
let's take this. Assam government using
its special power 1950 act that allows
Assam to expel Bangladesh without any
court or tribunal. Some are now shouting
some are now shouting human rights. But
what about mine? Why are you inside my
house in the first place? What's my
opinion? Okay, I'm not aware of this
1950 act or whatever it is. But if Assam
is now preparing to expel illegal
Bangladeshi infiltrators,
I would very much welcome that step.
Right? Anybody who is inside India
illegally has to be
deported, expelled from India. As simple
as that. India is not a damala like they
say, right? Only Indian citizens have
the right to live in India. If the
Bangladeshes have a problem in their
country, they can change their country
for the better. This is not their land.
We have created a separate nation for
them. They should be sent back there. So
if this is happening, I will be very
pleased about it.
All right people, let me now end the
live stream. That's and we have now
crossed two hours 30 minutes. All right
people, thank you so much for all the
questions. It was really fun. I I think
that we had some very interesting and
nice questions today. And let's continue
this in the future live stream. So next
weekend, next Sunday, I will do an ask
me a budget live stream in which I will
take questions about any topic, not only
geopolitics. Okay. And we shall do that.
And okay, we we have some more
questions. One one last question. VSvs
says, I have actually met someone named
Muhammad Vishnu, [laughter]
Indonesian, right? The Indonesians have
the most fantastic names. they have
refused to give up their Hindu identity
their their you know pre-Islamic
identity and they have kind of merged
that with the new Islamic name. So
Muhammad Vishnu is kind of that's the
kind of name you can find in Indonesia.
I suppose it will it will offend Muslims
as well as Hindus
but yeah that's Indonesia for you.
Fantastic nation. All right people thank
you so much for the questions. Keep
learning, keep asking questions, keep
raising your standards, and I shall see
you very soon in the next live stream.
Take care everybody. See you soon.